>> Ben Nham: Hi I'm Ben Nham.
I'm an engineer on the iPhone Performance team.
This is Advanced Performance Optimization
on iPhone OS Part 2.
Yesterday, we had Part 1 where we talked about making
your animations fluid, making your app responsive
and also optimizing the power usage of your app.
So if you didn't get a chance to go to that yesterday,
I highly recommend you take a look at that on video.
Today, we're going to be talking
about working with data efficiently.
And we're going to focus on working with that data both
in memory data structures and also taking that data
and putting it on and off disk using
serialization and deserialization routines.
We're going to focus on a few main themes.
The first is measurement tools.
We want you to be able to use our tools to find hot spots
in your code and then use those same tools to verify
that any fix you've made has actually
had the desired impact.
The next is mental models.
We want you to build up some intuition about
how the system is put together and how it works.
So you can preemptively write perform at code.
And finally, there are a lot of frameworks on our system.
So we're going to over a few of the best
practices for using these frameworks.
We're going to start by talking about how to use memory
efficiently and then move on to talking about how
to use the foundation framework
to manipulate data efficiently.
We'll talk about how to profile the file system to make sure
you get the maximum amount of I/O speed from your device.
Then move on to working with large datasets and databases.
And finally, making sure your application works well
with those large datasets and scales
to ever larger sizes of data.
So let's start with memory.
iOS isn't a desktop OS.
iOS devices aren't desktop devices.
As you can see in the chart, there's less memory
in an iOS device than on a desktop device.
In addition, there are some architectural
differences between iOS and the desktop OS.
For example, we have virtual memory
but we have no swap file.
This actually has some interesting
implications that we'll get into later.
There are also some features in iOS
that are not present on the desktop
such as low memory notifications
which you have to handle gracefully.
So let's take a look at a 128-megabyte
device such as the iPhone 3G.
You can see that there are a lot of processes and
applications that are running in the background
which you don't really have any control over that
are using memory even if your app isn't running.
So in this example, a certain amount of
memory is wired in by the kernel depending
on how much file activity or network activity you have.
It could be a little more or a little less.
There's always 12 megabytes allocated by the graphics card.
Some amount of memory used by Daemons.
Some may go away such as the sinking Daemons.
Some of them stay around forever such as the ones
that listen to your phone calls or listen on--
[laughter] the ones that listen on waiting for your
phone calls so you can listen to your phone calls.
Of course, there's other programs even on iPhone 3G
which can run all the time such as phone, mail, iPad,
and especially Safari which if you load a complex
web page can really take up quite a bit of memory.
So your app might be asked to launch and
run in a pretty limited memory window.
So it really pays to use memory efficiently.
So let's go over a few of the vocabulary
terms that you'll have to understand
to be able to really use our memory tools well.
Let's start with Paging.
Your process is split into 4 kilobyte chunks called
pages and those pages can be either nonresident,
resident and clean, or resident and dirty.
Page is resident if it's in physical memory.
If it's nonresident, it's not using physical memory.
And when you touch that nonresident
page, the kernel will take a page fault
and bring that nonresident page into physical memory.
Once that page is resident, it can either be clean or dirty.
If it's dirty, it's probably anonymous memory.
In other words, it just came out of thin air.
For example, malloc memory.
There's no file backing it at least on iOS so
that means that once a resident page is dirty,
it just stays around forever until you
deallocate it or your application quits.
So it's really important to keep
your dirty memory usage down.
There's also file-backed memory such as the memory that
backs your code or if you explicitly memory map to file.
And generally, this stays clean unless you modify it.
And what that means is that the kernel can
drop references to those pages at will.
So it's relatively free to use clean memory.
Now if you use too much dirty memory,
it'll actually crowd out the clean memory
that you have and that includes code pages.
So if you use too much dirty memory, it turns
out that just bringing in the code needed
to execute your program could take longer.
So let's go through an example and just as a caveat,
some of these examples are a little dependent
on your memory allocator but as a
simplification, most of these concepts are true.
So in this case I've allocated two
pages from my malloc allocator.
I've use valloc here which actually gives a page
align address but otherwise it's the same as malloc.
So at first, those two pages are nonresident.
They're not taking up any physical memory.
As soon as I write to-- for example
the first byte in the first page,
that page turns from nonresident into a resident dirty page.
So it's going to stick around until
either my app exits or I free this memory.
And similarly if I modify the second
page, it will take a page fault.
It will be brought into physical memory and that page
will turn from nonresident into resident and dirty.
With file-backed memory, if we map it
read-only which is the general case.
If we explicitly map this file in
this example which is two-pages long
into memory using dataWithContentsOfMappedFile.
Again, those pages start out as nonresident if we
don't actually access the data from those pages.
The moment we take any data from the first page, we're
going to bring the data from the file into memory
and that page turns from nonresident to resident and clean.
And similarly, the moment we reference any data
on the second page, we'll take another page fault
and that page turns from nonresident to
resident and clean in physical memory.
So where these concepts are really
useful are in our VM Tracker tool.
This is part of the allocations template in Instruments
and these VM snapshots basically take a snapshot
of you virtual memory usage out of
particular point in time in your application.
You can either ask Instruments to snapshot
automatically at a time interval or by default,
you actually have to trigger the snapshot
manually by clicking the snapshot Now button.
As a word of caution, this actually works best in the
simulator right now in our particular build of iOS 4.
So once you've taken these samples,
you'll get different samples over time.
And what you're really looking for are
you'll see the different regions of memory
in your application which we'll go over in a second.
But what you're really looking for is
growing dirty memory usage over time.
So in this case, I've started with 16 megabytes.
I took another snapshot a little while
later and now I have 20 megabytes
and now a little while later, I have 24 megabytes used.
So this is indicative of perhaps a memory leak.
Next we want to see which region was growing
in size, in this case, the malloc large region.
So as you can see it's growing in size over time.
So this is sort of indicating to you that this is
probably a region of memory that you want to focus on.
So if you see malloc growing, we have a lot
of great tools to help you deal with that.
There's the allocations template, the leaks template,
those are all great for looking for leaks in your heap.
If you have Growing dirty_DATA, that's pretty unusual.
Those are generally global variables that you've modified.
So if you do have global variables, try to make sure
if they're constant, that they're really constant
and then we'll put them into a read-only region.
If you see Core Animation growing up
over time, you might have a view leak
because each view is backed by Core Animation layer.
And just as a final note, if you see TC malloc
taking up about 200 kilobytes in your application,
you shouldn't be worried because that's fixed.
JavaScript core uses that to execute
JavaScript and it always takes at least
around 200 kilobytes even if you're not using a web view.
I'm not going to have time to talk about all
these other memory measurement tools we had.
We had an advanced memory analysis with Instruments
talk yesterday, that you should take a look at on video
to learn more about these tools, there's
the leaks template, the allocations template
and the zombies template which runs on the simulator.
These help you find leaks.
They help you find back traces for every single memory
allocation you've made in you applications lifetime
and they also help you find any
references to over released memory.
So please take a look at that talk if
you want to learn more about these tools.
What I'm going to focus on is something
that's unique to iOS 4 if you're coming
through the desktop and that's low memory warnings.
If your application or perhaps the cumulative effect of all
the applications on the system, use too much dirty memory,
a low memory warning will be fired and you have to
respond to this low memory warning in a graceful way.
So let's go over how this works.
As a total dirty memory in the system gets to a certain
threshold, your application will receive a warning.
If it gets to another threshold, then you'll get
another warning and background apps will exit
as we try to free up memory for your app.
As you continue using dirty memory, for
example if you a leak that eventually will get
to a critical threshold that can kill your app.
So when you get a low memory warning, make sure
to release any objects that you can release,
anything that can be reconstructed, anything that's cached.
Don't ask the user to restart the app or restart the device.
So there are a few places where you
can respond to low memory warnings.
If you have-- or if you're using UIView
controllers, override viewDidUnload.
Your app delegate will get an
applicationDidReceiveMemoryWarning callback
and any object can register for a UIApplication
DidReceiveMemoryWarningNotification.
Now I'm going to go over overriding
viewDidUnload in a bit more detail,
because this can be a bit tricky
if you're new to the platform.
When view controllers get a memory warning, if they're not
at the top of the navigation stack or if they're obscured
in some way, they'll automatically release their views.
But if you've retained subviews in some instance variables
or some outlets, you have to release those subviews for us.
Let's go over an example.
Suppose I have this navigation controller based app.
At the bottom of the view controller
hierarchy, we have a ComposeViewController.
And suppose I click on that photo and
slide a PhotoViewController on top.
And now we get a memory warning.
Well the ComposeViewController when it gets a
memory warning because it's not visible on screen,
it'll automatically release the
view associated with it for you.
But if you've retained the subviews
here, in this case, these are IBOutlets,
these button labels and textViews, those won't go away.
You have to manually release those in viewdidUnload.
So assuming I have these four outlets here, titleLabel,
locationLabel, textView, imageButton as properties,
in my viewDidUnload, to properly respond to the memory
warning, I'm going to set each of these properties to nil
and as a side effect, that release my
references to each of these subviews.
So now, when my ComposeViewController gets a memory warning,
it'll automatically release the view associated with it
and then our viewDidUnload will release the remaining
references to the subviews and that's what we want.
So it's really important that you test
out low memory warnings in the simulator.
We've seen a lot of interesting behavior in responding
to low memory warnings even in the labs here.
So make sure you test this out in many different ways.
I just want to make a quick note
about interacting with multitasking.
Of course, we've had several sessions on multitasking
here but when your application goes into the background,
we don't preemptively, for example,
send a low memory warning.
We let you make the tradeoff.
And the tradeoff is multitasking is
supposed to be a fast app switching.
So we want users to be able to
get back into your app quickly.
But on the other hand, when your app is
in the background, it's using up memory.
So you should try to release any easily reconstructed
resources in you applicationDidEnterBackrground call.
On the other hand, if you release some
resource that's really expensive to recreate,
that kind of defeats the purpose of
fast app switching because then you have
to expensively recreate it when you become foreground.
So this is a tradeoff you'll have to make.
Make sure you play with this a
bit and release as many resources
as you can possibly do reasonably
without making fast app switching slow.
Now, I just want to talk a bit about image memory as well.
In the past, we've had a slide here that has a
chart that doesn't really go over all the subtleties
of image memory and really can cause a lot of confusion.
So I've alleviated by removing the chart.
And I'm just going to give you this general advice.
If you use UIImage imageNamed, use that for read-only
resources that come out of your app bundle and are used
as say background images for buttons
or you're going to use them to draw
on the table view cells, things
that are used in UI elements.
For everything else, UIImage, imageWithContentsOfFile
is generally good enough.
We've removed a lot of the performance
differences between these methods
so that this general advice is generally good enough.
One thing I'd like to point out is that in iOS 4,
we've made public the ImageIO framework
which has been on OS X since Tiger.
And one of the nice features of ImageIO is if
you're creating thumbnails of large images,
it can do so quickly in both-- or
efficiently in both space and time.
So to use this, you create a CGUmageSourceRef which
encapsulates the deserialization of the image.
And then you pass in this options dictionary which asks
the image source to create a thumbnail and also the size
of that thumbnail and out pops a
CGImageRef that's the thumbnail.
And this is as I said efficiently uses memory so that if
you create a thumbnail out of a say 2 megapixel image,
you'll use much less memory than if you
just deserialize that 2 megapixel image
and then use ports to draw that into a 44 by 44 context.
So if you want to know more about this,
refer to the Creating a Thumbnail Image
section of the Image I/O Programming Guide.
This is a code snippet but that it'll go over all
the caveats of using CGImageSource in this way.
So in summary, drive down the dirty
memory usage of your app.
It causes memory warnings.
It crowds out clean memory that could be
used to for example execute code in your app.
Respond to memory warnings correctly.
And release resources as necessary
when entering a background.
We have a few additional user guides but really
what I'd really urge you to do is to take a look
at Advanced Memory Analysis with
Instruments talk on video afterwards.
So next let's talk about Foundation.
Foundation has a lot of the objects
we care about including NSObject.
But let's go over some of the collection
performance characteristics
of the collections inside Foundation
starting with NSMutableArray.
Arrays have pretty textbook performance
characteristics in our system
but there is one unique performance characteristics that
I want to point out which is that inserting or deleting
at the beginning of an array is amortized constant
time which means you can use an array as a queue
or as double ended queue pretty efficiently.
This is of course not true for most arrays you've probably
dealt with in the past if you're new to our framework.
So before rolling your own queue, you can try
NSMutableArray first and it probably will be good enough.
There is also another interesting thing which is
that if you insert 250,000 elements into your array,
it becomes a tree but if you did that, let us know.
Strings work a lot like arrays.
Indexed access is constant time.
It's going to be a load plus a load at an offset probably.
Inserting or deleting the middle is linear time.
Inserting or deleting at the end is constant time.
This is all pretty similar to any other mutable
string class you've probably dealt with in the past.
Dictionaries also work like most
other well-behaved dictionaries.
If you have a good hash function, all the major mutation
functions or lookup functions such as lookup, insertion,
replacement, removal, those are all constant time.
But with a bad hash function, you
turn your dictionary into an array.
And in particular, that means that
a lookup turns into a linear search.
So what do I mean by bad hash function?
If your return a constant value, that's a bad hash function.
If you return a random value, that's a broken hash function.
It's actually really hard to give good general advice about
hash functions because there are whole courses about how
to write optimal hash functions but most of you apply the
making custom objects that are compositions of objects
that we give you such as UIViews or arrays or dictionaries.
In this case, I have this example where we have this array
dict that has instance variables and array and a dictionary.
And of course we implement hash for you on
these objects efficiently and correctly.
So if you don't know any better, you can try just
XORing the hash of each of these instance variables
that you have and that's usually good enough.
In addition, you should make sure
the hash function runs quickly,
because as the dictionary grows we may have
to increase the size of the dictionary.
At which point, we have to rehash all
the existing values in the dictionary.
So stick to pretty fast operations
adding, shifting, masking or XORing.
And remember the API contract, when you call
-setObject:forKey, your key will be copied.
So respond to NSCopying in some same way.
In addition, objects that are equal
must return the same hash.
If you don't follow this, your dictionary won't work.
Now that we've talked about some of the
performance characteristics of these collections,
let's take a look at some of these
perhaps tips and tricks about how
to use this collections in the most performant way.
And the first is if you're storing a lot of integers into
your collection, one way to do it is by boxing each integer
into an NS number and passing it on to
your NSSet or NSMutableArray or so forth.
But you can actually bypass this integer boxing
step by using the correct data structure.
So NSIndexSet is built to work with integers natively.
In addition, core foundation collections can work
with pointer size integers if you cast those integers
into pointers by passing NULL into the
callbacks parameter of the constructor.
So in this example, to create an array that stores
integers natively without boxing to NSNumbers,
I can call CFArrayCreateMutable using default allocator
with no capacity restriction and NULL as the callbacks.
And I just cast my integer into a pointer and I can
just add and remove and modify my array without boxing.
So if you do this enough, it can actually add up.
These timings are taken from the iPhone 3G.
If you box and store 1000 NSNumbers
into a set, it takes 30 milliseconds.
If you don't box the integers and just store them natively
into a mutable index set or a mutable
set, it's 10 times faster.
So these are one of those things that might add up over
time if you box a lot of integers in your application.
Next, let's talk about bulk operations.
I've told you that some of these methods such as
objectAtIndex or characterAtIndex are efficient.
They're constant time.
But there is a message sending overhead to
calling these methods over and over again.
So for example, if you want to call NSString
characterAtIndex over and over again,
perhaps you should instead call getCharacters
range and just inspect the range you care about.
Get that range into a C buffer and inspect
the buffer using standard C indexing.
That can be up to 3 times faster.
Even better, hopefully there's a method inside these
classes that does exactly what you want such as
if you want prefix search, you might just want
to call hasPrefix rather than writing your own.
So make sure you inspect the API and
select the highest level API possible
because it's probably already implemented
in the most performant way for you.
One thing I want to point out in particular is that strings
now have regular expression support finally in iOS 4.
We've made them really easy for
you to use regular expressions.
You can use the existing NSString methods and pass this
NSRegularExpression search option and all of a sudden,
your substring search turns into
a regular expression search.
And this is great for one-off searches.
But if you're going to look for the same
pattern in many different strings, use--
create an NSRegularExpression object
and use the enumerateMatchesInString
options range using block method instead.
And the reason for that is parsing
a regular expression takes some time
and sets up some state that you
don't want to continually pay.
If you use the regular expression object, you
additionally had these options NSMatchingReportProgress.
We'll call this block back even if you don't get
a match periodically and you can write to the stop
out parameter the-- you can write yes to the stop
out parameter to stop the search prematurely.
Regular expressions are an example of objects
which are a bit expensive to reinitialize
over and over again with the same parameters.
They are examples of objects that you should keep
around if you're going to use again and again.
Date formatters and number formatters
are the other usual example of this.
So here's an example where we have a table view
cell that shows a month and one way to do this is
to just create a table-- create a date formatter
for every table view cell that comes on screen.
Set its date format to the month
day format and use that formatter
to format the month string and
this works but it's not performant.
Instead, you should lazily create that date formatter
if you're going to use it over and over again.
In this sample code, the first time you call
monthFormatter, it will create the monthFormatter.
Every subsequent time, it'll return the
monthFormatter that's already created
and then we can use this function
to format our date performantly.
There are some gotchas with doing this.
In particular in iOS 4, the user can change
their locale without exiting your app.
So you have to listen
to the NSCurrentLocaleDidChangeNotification
if you're caching date formatters.
In this case, I've just released and
nilled out the formatter I created
so that it'll be recreated after
the user changes their locale.
In addition, date and number formatters aren't thread-safe
so you need to either use locking or create a separate one
for each thread that you're using these cache formatters on.
But do note that regular expressions and data detectors
are thread-safe so you don't have to worry about locking
or creating different ones for different threads there.
So again, just to drive this point home, if you
would take 100 date formatters and use each of them
to format the same date one time, it's about five to
six times slower that taking a single day formatter
and formatting-- and using that to format 100 dates.
Next, let's talk about property lists.
These are really convenient way of serializing
and deserializing object graphs in Foundation.
They're so convenient that you might be tempted to
use the right to file atomically methods on each
of these collections, arrays, dictionaries, and strings.
These are really convenient but you shouldn't
use them because they produce XML plists.
And XML plists are two to three times
slower to decode that binary plists.
So if you create plist at run time, make sure you
use NSPropertyListSerialization and explicitly pass
in the NSPropertyListBinaryFormat_v1_0-- that'll
create a binary plist from your object graph.
And then from that, the data you get back,
you can write that out to disk as you please.
[ Pause ]
So plists are not an incremental format.
What that means is if you want to access a single value
out of a plist, we have to take that entire object graph
into the plist, bring in some memory
before you can access that one element.
Similarly, when you're writing out the plist,
if you modify a single element in the plist,
we have to write out the entire object
graph just to signify that one change.
So plists are great for small sets of objects, dozens of
objects, maybe hundreds of objects, no more than that.
If you need to really encode a really large object
graph, you should probably be looking at a database
or Core Data because those will be incremental.
They'll only bring the data you care about into memory
and only write the changes that you made out to disk.
Related to plist is NSCoding.
NSCoding has the advantage that it's
not restricted to plistable types.
It's-- You can define your own archiver essentially,
or your own encoder to encode your own custom types.
And again this is generally not an incremental format.
To access one object out of an archive, you generally have
to bring-- deserialize all the objects out of that archive.
Keep this to small object graphs.
Don't encode thousands of objects using NSCoding and this
is a time profile I actually pulled from a top 10 app.
I know this was quitting pretty slowly and you can
actually see it's taking about 400 milliseconds
to archive some large object graph at quit time.
So really runtime profiler, make sure you're not blocked
on CPU and encoding or decoding these large object graphs
with NSCoding because they can take
quite a while to encode or decode.
Even if you don't explicitly use NSCoding, you're
probably implicitly using them by using NIBs.
And the way you can keep the NSCoding usage down
in NIBs just to make sure your NIBs are lean,
don't put objects in your NIB that aren't
associated with the files owner of that NIB.
In iOS 4, we've added this new class called
UINib that actually lets you deserialize objects
from the same NIB repeatedly over
and over again much faster.
This is mostly used for table view cell NIBs.
So in this example, I took this table view cell from the
advanced table view cells example and that's on the left.
On the right, you can see the NIB
that that table view cell came from.
So in our tableView cellForRowAtIndexPath, we have to
load the cell from the NIB if it's not in the reuse queue.
So the previous way of doing this would be the-- called the
Foundation method, loadNibNamed, owner, options on NSBundle
and this works if you're only viewing it once, if
you're only creating an object out of this NIB once.
This is perfectly fine.
But if you're creating for example a table
view cell, you're probably going to create
that table view cell out of the NIB many times.
So you want to use the UINib class to cache some
state associated with repeatedly instantiating NIBs
and ask the UINib instance for the objects in that NIB
instead of asking the bundle for the objects in that NIB.
And again, this takes-- this makes NIB loading
about 33 percent faster if you're going
to load the same resource out of a NIB over and over again.
So in summary, most of the Foundation types have
pretty good performance if you use them correctly.
So understand the API.
Make sure you call the highest level API possible.
Avoid reinitializing expensive classes
such as date formatters over and over again
if you're going to use them over and over again.
And finally, make sure you restrict your use plist
and NSCoding to relatively small object graphs.
We ship a lot of user guides with our SDK that let you know
how to use collections, property lists, NSCoding and NIBs,
so take a look at those if you have more questions.
We also had an Understanding Foundation session yesterday
that you should look at on video
if you're new to Foundation.
Next, let's talk about the filesystem.
The first thing you should probably do if you think you have
a filesystem performance issue is run the System Usage tool.
And what this does is it prints out a list
of all the filesystem related system
calls your application has made along
with the backtrace that caused that system call.
So this is a great place to look for unexpected I/O and
figure out what backtrace caused that unexpected I/O.
There's one caveat with this which is that if you're
using memory mapped files, it doesn't yet show bytes
that were read in-- caused by paging
in bytes from the memory mapped file.
So some best practices for working with the Filesystem,
you should definitely test your
application on different types of devices.
We've advertised that the 3GS is two times
faster than the 3G in CPU and there are--
also very significant performance
differences in read and write performance.
So you really need to make sure you test application
on an iPhone 3G if you're targeting an iPhone 3G.
In addition, if you're doing really long blocking
I/Os just as with any other long blocking operation,
move them off the main thread using
any of our threading APIs,
Grand Central Dispatch, NSOperations queues and so forth.
But if you are really doing a really long
I/O, say with NSData dataWithContentsOfFile,
you might not want to call that
method with a really large file.
For example, if I call dataWithContentsOfFile
on a 10 megabyte file,
we're going to allocate a 10 megabyte
buffer inside your application.
We're going to block your application until we can read all
those 10 megabytes into that buffer in your application.
Instead, you should probably use
dataWithContentsofMappedFile
and that will return almost immediately.
And we'll use the virtual memory subsystem
to demand page in data from that file
as you touch the data as we talked
about earlier in the talk.
In addition, if we you want to use standard
seat based I/O, you can use NSFileHandle.
One last point here is that if you're repeatedly opening
or statting a path inside the system usage instrument,
you probably shouldn't do that because opening or
statting paths incurs an additional permissions check
above the usual UNIX permissions
check in our system where we base--
we recheck whether your app has access to that path.
So don't recursively enumerate a
directory with say a thousand files
and ask for the modification date on all those files.
That's probably going to be a bit slow.
To actually get paths into Filesystem, we have a few APIs,
NSBundle gives you paths inside your read-only app bundle.
If you want to store user defaults, you
probably should use NSUserDefaults rather
than any home-grown default system
because those will be backed up for you.
If you want writable paths, usually you'll
use NSSearchPathForDirectoriesInDomain
and you should pick the right directory
for the type of data you're storing.
If you're storing persistent user-related data,
use NSDocumentDirectory because it gets backed up.
It stays between launches and it's always there.
NSUserDefaults is the same.
If you just need some data that can be reconstructed,
you should probably put in NSCachesDirectory
because it won't be backed up and won't
affect the user backup performance.
And finally, if you just need to scribble somewhere for this
particular invocation of the app, use NSTemporaryDirectory.
One thing I want to point is that you should
not be constructing arbitrary paths outside
of your application sandbox and writing to them.
That's a system protected interface
and it's not guaranteed to work.
Even if you can write to a particular path outside
of your sandbox now and in the next release,
you might not be able to and your app will break, the
customers will get angry, all sorts of sadness will ensue.
So don't do that.
So in summary, start with the System Usage
tool, look for any unexpected I/Os and figure
out from the backtrace what caused those unexpected I/Os.
If you have really large files, try to pick an incremental
format or you can try using the memory mapped file option
to demand page in that large file as necessary.
And as with any other long lasting operation,
perform your long I/Os off the main thread.
Next, let's talk about manipulating
large datasets and databases.
We really like databases because they let
you bring just the information you care
about into memory rather than entire data set into memory.
There're also additional features that databases give
you, transactional storage, isolation, durability,
those are all great properties for a persistent data store.
And we really recommend you use Core Data if possible if
you're creating a new application because we've taken a lot
of the grudge work of using databases in Core Data.
There is automatic schema management.
There is also iPhone specific enhancements for
example table view section loading is faster
in Core Data because we especially optimized it.
The Native SQLite library is available if you
want to work with databases directly but just note
that it's much more low level and requires more care.
No matter what framework you choose
though, you must have the same data model.
So understand some of the basic concepts in data modeling.
I've referenced this object modeling guide inside
the Cocoa Fundamentals Guide which talks about some
of the key concepts such as one-to-one relationships,
one-to-many relationships, many-to-many relationships.
You should understand these if you want to
be able to create a performant data model.
What I'm going to talk about a bit more is actually
SQLite because we haven't had as much coverage of SQLite
and we know that some of you are
still using it rather than Core Data.
If you are using Core Data, please watch the Understanding
Performance in Core Data session from yesterday.
So the first thing you should do if you have a performance
issue in SQLite is to run the sqlite3_profile function
and this will install a profiling method which calls back
the profile function every time a statement executes along
with an estimate of how long that statement took to execute.
So in this case, the profile function just prints out
the SQL statement along with how long it took to execute.
This is really helpful for finding
out if you have a lot of slow queries
or maybe just one really slow query
that you should be concentrating on.
In addition, you should keep in mind that prepared
statements in SQLite are really little programs.
Every time you call SQLite3 prepare, you're really
compiling a little program for a SQLite to interpret.
So you can actually even see the
instructions of this program
by prepending the statement with
EXPLAIN in the SQLite shell tool.
So what this means is you probably don't want
to recompile programs over and over again.
So likewise, you don't want to prepare
statements over and over again.
So if you're going to use a prepared
statement repeatedly, keep it in memory.
Conversely, if you're not going to use the prepared
statement over and over again, you should release it.
We've actually seen some applications that keep every
single prepared statement they've ever created in memory
and then 1,000, 2,000, 3,000 statements later, the app
gets terminated because that memory was never released.
So if you used sqlite3_profile to find an offending
query and you've prepared your query efficiently,
the next thing you want to do is use EXPLAIN QUERY PLAN or
EXPLAIN to actually understand what SQLite is doing execute
that query and you could do this by
opening your database on your Mac
and prepending the statement with
EXPLAIN QUERY PLAN or EXPLAIN.
And one of the things you'll notice when you do this
is that if you switch the order of tables in a JOIN,
you might not be able to affect the order in which SQLite
traverses the table, so this might be something you want
to play with if you have a JOIN that's slow.
In addition, watch out for transient tables.
If you explain a statement and you see an OpenEphemeral
instruction, you've created a temporary table
for the lifetime of that particular statement.
So these can cause pretty big performance issues if you've
created a temporarily table of many thousands of rows in it.
Usually these come from sorting a
table without an index or subselects
and that can cause the first sqlite3_step
to take a pretty long time.
So let's go over an example.
Here we have a sample schema from a music player.
There's a track.
Each track has an album.
Albums could have many tracks.
Each track also has an artist and
artists could have authored many tracks.
So without any indices, a Naive
query plan might look like this.
I open my database up in the SQLite
tool on my Mac and I EXPLAIN QUERY PLAN,
SELECT * FROM Track WHERE AlbumID is a
particular album ordered by AlbumOrder
and what that means is select all the tracks
in an album and sort that album by track order.
That's a pretty simple and reasonable query.
Without any indices, it's telling me that it's going to
do a table scan of track and what that's going to look
like is actually we're going to go over every row
in that table and then we're going to find the rows
that match the album we care about,
in this case AlbumID of 2.
We're going to move that result set into
a transient table and then we're going
to sort it to satisfy the order by criterion.
And that's pretty inefficient.
So perhaps you've worked with databases
before and, you know, well,
I have a where clause on this albumID,
I need an index on albumID.
And that's great because now when we look for all
albums with AlbumID=2, we're got a logarithmic--
in logarithmic time, we're going to jump to AlbumID=2 in the
index and we're going to use that to select all the albums,
all the tracks in that album from the track table.
But again, we've iterated over those tracks in unsorted
order so we have to create a temporary table that holds
that entire result set and then sort all those
results before giving you back the pointer
to that first result in this result set.
So there's a lot going on there before
that first sqlite3_step returned.
So in this particular case, what you really want is
an index that sorts all the tracks first by the album
and then by the track order within that album.
So here we've created an index,
TrackAlbumIDOrderIndex ON Track(AlbumID, AlbumOrder).
And now when we try to select all the tracks in the
album, ordered by the track order in that album,
we'll first look at the index and in logarithmic
time, we'll jump to the first track in that album
and now we can just iterate over
the track table in sorted order.
And you can see that EXPLAIN QUERY
PLAN has showed this to us by saying,
table track with index the index we created
ORDER BY which means that we're iterating
over to the track table using this index and also
using that index to satisfy the order by criterion.
[ Pause ]
The last thing I want to point out here is
that the query planner also works with Joins.
So, if you have a query that joins two tables,
it'll actually tell you the order in
which it's visiting those two tables.
I won't go over this in detail but as
you can se in this particular query plan,
we visit the track table using an index and then we join
on to the artist table using the
built-in primary key index of artist.
One last concept that I'm going to
talk about in SQLite is the page cache.
When you have a SQLite database file, it's split into a set
of contiguous pages, each generally 4 kilobytes in length.
And it's just like any other file,
just a contiguous array of bytes.
But logically, what those contiguous array of bytes mean is
a set of B-Trees for each table and index in your database.
So, each of the nodes in that B-Tree is a separate page.
When we want to actually access any page in that B-Tree, we
actually have to bring it into memory into a data structure
that SQLite maintains for you called the page cache.
So in this case, if we are doing an
in order traversal of this B-Tree,
we're actually going to overwrite
the existing contents of what was
in the page cache with the pages that are in this table.
So, what this means is that if you want to
access say a byte from a table in SQLite,
what you're actually doing is you're bringing
the entire page around that byte into memory.
So, you should keep this in mind when performing operations
with SQLite, I/O is done in page-sized increments.
In particular, if you're updating or modifying the
database in any way, you should surround your updates
with transactions, because otherwise, each UPDATE
or INSERT will modify a page in the page cache.
It'll journal out or copy the page that's being modified
from the database file out to a journal file, and finally,
you'll be able to modify the page you cared about.
So, there's a lot of IO going on, a lot of page-sized
IO going on for just your little small update.
In addition, because this page cache
is a fixed size, 1 megabyte by default,
you shouldn't use your database as a filesystem.
You shouldn't store large BLOBs inside your database.
For example, assume you stored a 1 megabyte BLOB
inside your database, if your page cache is 1 megabyte,
you've actually just blown out the entire page
cache and replaced it with that 1 megabyte BLOB,
and that will make your joins slower
and your subsequent selects slower.
In addition, because SQLite is
journaled, you'll pay a double cost
in journaling the data before actually writing it to disk.
So, instead of using the database as a filesystem, you
should probably store pointers to the filesystem instead,
and store those large BLOBs in the filesystem.
And just to drive this point home, if you don't
surround your batch updates with transactions,
you can really shoot yourself in the foot.
In this case, I took a pretty simple database
and made a thousand updates and left it
in the standard autocommit mode, which means one transaction
for every modification, and I did 24 megabytes of I/O.
Whereas if I surrounded those same 1000 updates with
a single transaction, I did 40 kilobytes of I/O.
So, really look out for this.
You'll actually see this in the System Usage instrument.
If you see a lot of journal or a SQLite database activity,
make sure you've surrounded your
modifications with transactions.
So in summary, if you're using
databases, use Core Data if possible.
It takes out a lot of the grudge work for you.
If you are using SQLite directly and you have a performance
problem, first start by using a sqlite3_profile to figure
out what statement is causing the performance issue.
Once you know the statement that's causing the
performance issue, use EXPLAIN QUERY PLAN to figure
out what SQLite is doing to execute that query.
If you're doing a lot of modifications,
make sure your transactions--
make sure you're using transactions
to surround the modifications
so you amortize the cost of all those page-sized I/Os.
If you want more resources on using SQLite or Core Data
directly, we had a few sessions on Core Data yesterday.
In addition, if you're using SQLite directly, I highly
recommend you take a look at the YouTube video by D.
Richard Hipp that-- where he gives
an introduction to SQLite.
He wrote the framework, so he knows how to use it.
And there's also a lot of documentation on the website for
all the key features, journaling, file format and so forth.
So, take a look at that if you need more help.
Finally, let's talk about making your
app scale well with large data sets.
Your app could be faced with an extremely
large data set, thousands of items.
And so, to make this-- your app perform well in the
face of that data set, make sure you're thinking
about the minimum amount of work needed
to make the critical methods fast.
And as an example, we'll take a
look at the Contacts application.
So, I took a few timings of launching Contacts with 30
contacts, 300 contacts and 3000 contacts on an iPhone 3G.
And as you can see, the launch time is pretty much
the same no matter how much data you throw at it.
Now, if your app deals with a lot of data,
you should probably do this with your app,
increase the data size by an order
of magnitude over and over again,
and see how your launch time or
other critical operations respond.
Ideally, you want something that looks like this,
something that stays relatively constant even
as you're increasing the size of your data set.
So, in launching applications,
there are a few critical methods.
Most of the performance is driven by this
tableView that you see when you launch Contacts.
The first thing you have to do is tell
the tableView how many sections are
in your tableView and the title for those sections.
You also have to tell the tableView
the number of rows in each section.
If you have an index bar as in Contacts, you
have to give the tableView the index bar.
And finally, for each of these visible cells on screen,
you're going to have to load and create the tableView cells.
So, let's go over how to make each of these operations
fast or at least how we've made them fast in Contacts.
So, to load sections quickly, the naive approach would
be to take your entire data set, suck it into memory,
and then post-process them into sections.
And that works for small data sets, but of course
it grows linearly with the size of your data set.
If you have 10 times more data, it's going to take
at least 10 times longer to load your sections.
So, a better idea if you're faced with large
data sets is to cache those sections counts
to make this critical section count method fast.
In Contacts, we actually have a separate table that we
maintain by triggers that maintains those section counts.
It's actually a little hard to do right if
you're targeting multiple localizations.
So, take a look at the DerivedProperty example on
our Developer Sample Code website to get an idea
of how to deal with differing localizations.
Good news for Core Data users is they
get them-- they get this for free.
If you pass in the-- if you use the cache name parameter
from NSFetchedResultsController initWithFetchRequest
to managedObjectContext setionNameKeyPath cacheNname,
it'll save those section counts off to a side file outside
of the database, actually, and use that
cache file if it matches your fetch request.
Otherwise, it'll cache the results of the fetch request
so that the next time you make that fetch request,
maybe the next time you'd launch the
application, it'll be really fast.
Next, we need to load the index bar quickly.
You can do what we do in Contacts and cheat.
You could always just load the same index bar.
Even if you have no Contacts, you'll
notice that we always put A to Z and number
as your index bar, and that's perfectly fine.
Otherwise, if your index bar is going to change
based on the number of sections you have,
anything you've done to make section loading faster
will also make your index bar loading faster.
And finally, let's look at loading the cells
that are visible on the screen quickly.
And this is where, if you're using a database, some of the
profiling tools that I showed you earlier might help you.
What you really don't want to do is to
bring in the entire table all at once just
to retrieve one cell's worth of information.
So, what we do in Contacts is we actually do something
where we select the Contacts and
batches as you're scrolling along.
It turns out LIMIT and OFFSET is
not particularly fast in SQLite.
There's a pretty long section on this on the website.
But if you're iterating over a
small index, it generally works OK.
There's also a document on the website called the--
that describes the scrolling cursor
method that you might want to use.
So, if you're having trouble loading cells quickly,
for example, you use time profile or you find
that you're spending a lot of time in tableView
cellForRowAtIndexPath, take a look at these documents.
And again, this is really where
proper indices will help you.
If you have a proper index, hopefully, you only have
to touch very little data to get
one cell's worth of information.
If you don't have a proper index, you do a transient sort
over your entire result set just to get the first table cell
on the tableView, then it's probably
going to be a bit slower.
So, in summary, test and profile you apps with different
data set sizes, and only bring in the data necessary
to satisfy the critical methods in your application.
I've only looked at one example here.
This is really something that you've got to do that's
custom to your app to figure out what methods are critical,
and make sure you're only doing what's necessary.
So, in summary, reduce the dirty memory usage in your app.
Dirty memory causes low memory warnings.
It crowds out clean memory that might be--
that you might be using for executing code.
Adhere to the Foundation API best practices.
Foundation is generally pretty performant,
but you do have to use it correctly
to get the maximum performance out of it.
If you have filesystem or database performance issues, use
our profiling tools to figure out where the bottlenecks are.
If you have a critical query or a critical file that's
taking a really long time to load, and hopefully,
that'll give you an idea of where to start to
make that critical query or file faster to load.
And finally, make sure to test your
apps on different types of devices
because each device has different
performance characteristics.
If you have more questions, please
contact our evangelist, Michael Jurewitz.
And you can always talk to us on the Developer Forums.
I want to point you to some of these related sessions.
These of course are all in the past, but
you can watch them on video afterwards.
We had a Performance Optimization on iPhone OS session,
that's more of a first timer session,
if you're new to the tools.
Please take a look at that.
We have a lot of demos there.
There's the first part of this talk,
it was yesterday where we talked
about animations and optimizing power and responsiveness.
If you want to learn to use the memory tools or
other instruments, attend these Instruments talks.
And finally, we have a Core Data talk if you
have Core Data performance issues and that's all.
[ Applause ]