>> Stuart Cheshire: Good morning ladies and gentlemen.
It's good to see you all here today.
My name is Stuart Cheshire and I'm the architect of Bonjour.
I'm going to be telling you today about Bonjour
and related technologies and particularly
about how it interacts with multitasking on iOS 4.
Let me ask how many people are here at their first WWDC.
Can I see a show of hands?
That is amazing.
That's more than half the room.
And how many are here for the first
time at a Bonjour presentation.
OK. Then I'm glad we have some overview because this is the
first time for I'd say about 80% of the people in the room.
In previous years, what I'm going to talk about is the
overview would have been the entire hour-long presentation.
We have a lot more stuff to talk about today so it's going
to be very condensed but I hope it'll give you the flavor
of what it's about and at least point you in the right
direction for more documentation to find out more details.
Rory McGuire, my colleague will be telling you about some
specific details of Bonjour on iPhone OS and will be talking
about some other developments because
Bonjour is not just a Mac technology.
It's not just an Apple technology.
We have Bonjour on Windows and there are many
third party products using Bonjour as well.
It is an open standard.
The source code is open source under the Apache
2 license and all the specifications of public.
We'll wrap up with some tips and reminders
of common mistakes that which developers make
so that you can avoid making the same mistakes.
So let's start with the high level goal.
TCP/IP, the technology of the internet clearly won out
against all the other wide area of technologies like DECnet
and XNS, X.25, ISDN and it was a great
achievement to build a global scale network.
But where it lacked was ease of
use and the canonical example I
like to give is you take a USB printer,
you take the cable, you plug it in.
Nobody has to type addresses and subnet masks and
configuration parameters to make that USB work.
And there's no technical reason why
IP can't be just as easy as that.
The only reason is that all the people working on it
in the early days were so focused on the challenge
of building a global network to rival the telephone system
that they totally neglected worrying about the details
of two computers connected with a cable
because that seems so trivial in comparison.
What we did with Bonjour and zero configuration
networking is to go back and fill in that missing piece.
So when you're designing your application
or your hardware product,
if you have any doubts about a certain
design decision, kind of mentally think,
if I plug it into USB, what would I expect.
We would like the same user experience with an Ethernet
cable or with Wi-Fi or with IP or with Bluetooth.
So that's the goal.
We want networking where you just plug it and it works.
This is how we achieve that goal.
And there are three legs of technology that make up the
foundation for Bonjour, zero configuration networking
and that foundation is what lets you developers write
applications where you can rely on networking being present
and functional and not have to worry about
a lot of failure modes that you used to have
and I'll start up with one of those failure modes.
DHCP is great.
We are not competing with DHCP at all and if you have a DHCP
server on the network handing out addresses, that's great.
But if you don't, if you just have two devices connected
with an Ethernet cable or some devices connected
to a simple Ethernet switch, then there's no DHCP server.
And in the past, most devices would just give up.
So you can't find DHCP server and refuse
to work until the user fix the problem.
Now for desktop computer with a screen and a
keyboard, that's annoying but it's not fatal
because the user can configure a manual address.
But for devices that don't have a screen and a keyboard,
for device like an AirPort Extreme Base Station
where it's only user interface for
controlling it is over the network.
It has got to get itself on the network.
Because if its network is misconfigured
so it can't communicate,
you have no way of communicating with it to fix that.
So IPv6 has link-local addressing.
Every IPv6 device configures itself a link-local address
on every interface which is not configured by the user.
The user can't break that so you can rely
on it to have an address and with RC3927,
we have the same thing in IPv4
and you've probably seen this now.
This is not new.
Ten years ago when we're talking about this, this was new.
These days everyone in the room is probably
familiar with those addresses 169.254
and that means the machine picked its own address because
it couldn't find the DHCP server to give it another address.
So this is a good start.
We can have two or three or five machines
all with self-assigned unique addresses
but it doesn't really help you if
you don't know what the address is
and nobody likes typing addresses especially IPv6 addresses.
With conventional IP, people are
used to using DNS host names.
So following a similar principle that we want to
stay as close as possible to our current practices,
we use Multicast DNS which uses the same naming syntax,
the same record types, the same resource record types
and the same packet format of standard
DNS but without a central server.
And every device on the network has a piece of software
which is the Multicast DNS responder
which knows that device its own name.
And when the client multicast a
query to every device on the network,
the one that recognizes its name says,
hey, that's me and it answers the query.
Now that's good.
That's got us to parity with what people expected of the
internet 10 years ago but you still have to know the name
to type and if you type it wrong, it
doesn't work and you don't really know why.
So we wanted to go one step beyond that
and that's the third item on this list
of technologies and that's service discovery.
Building on the Multicast DNS mechanisms, we
can also multicast queries to the network.
Not for specific host name but for type of service.
Say, I want to print.
What devices out there can meet that need for me?
What printers are out there that I can turn a printer up
too that results in sheets of printed paper coming out.
And that service discovery is the
third leg and that's the level that you
as developers will generally be interacting with this.
Because the addressing is handled by the OS, so unless
you're building hardware devices, you don't need to do that
and the host name lookup is an OS level function.
But if you are offering services on the network and
that means if you have a socket that's listening
or if you're making connections on the network, you'll
want to interact with the service discovery APIs
that Bonjour provides on the Mac, on
iOS, on Windows and on other platforms.
So here's an overview.
You have a piece of software that's
listening for connections.
That's great and you can make the user write down
the port number on a post-it note but it's better
to use the technology we have to
advertise that fact on the network.
When your service starts up or when the machine
wakes from sleep or when you connect the network,
it sends out a couple of announcement packets to let clients
that may be listening know that
this service is now on the network.
Now it's not continuously broadcasting its pockets
because that would add up to a lot of wasted bandwidth
but it does send out a few packets on startup.
Now suppose a client comes along
and were looking for that service.
The client will do a browse operation and these
APIs were available in C and in Cocoa and in Java,
in different languages, but they all have the
common property that you browse the services
and the server responds if it has
an instance of that service type.
So this lets the client build a list to
present to the user so the user can pick
which particular instance they want to connect to.
And then the second step is resolving that name
service to get the current IP address and port number
where that service can be reached and this
is a very important point with Bonjour.
Browsing and resolving are separate, other service
discovery protocols didn't make this separation
and the reason it's important is because, I'll
go back to the familiar example of printing.
Browsing the network defined which printers
are available and picking the one you're going
to use most of time is your default prints out.
It's an operation that people do relatively infrequently.
Some people may only do it once a year.
They pick a printer and then they don't change it at work.
But with DHCP, with link-local addressing, addresses and
ports can change overtime and if your printer preferences
on your machine have stored the address and
port number, that might not work tomorrow.
But the names are stable overtime.
So by storing the name and then resolving on
use, you get the current address information.
So this is very important, we'll come back to this later.
Browse to show the use of the list but then resolve a
connection time to find the most up-to-date information.
That was on the local network.
One of the questions we knew that would come up is,
well this is great on the local link
but what about across the internet.
What if I'm behind the NAT Gateway and the
answer is the same Bonjour APIs that work
with link-local Multicast DNS also work with
wide area Bonjour and the area where most
of you are probably most familiar with this, is this is the
underlying technology between Back to My Mac in MobileMe.
So when you're using screen sharing and file sharing to
access your machine across the other side of the country,
it's wide area Bonjour and the standard Bonjour APIs that
are doing that for you and if you have an application
that registers with Bonjour and browses with Bonjour,
then your application will work
planet-wide using Back to My Mac as well.
It's not just screen sharing and file sharing.
It supports all of your apps as well.
This is the API architecture.
On top of the kernel, we have a daemon called
mDNSResponder running and clients talk to that daemon
to advertise services and browse the services.
There are three main levels of API here not counting
Java and Python and Ruby and some of the other languages.
There's the dns_sd.h which is the
low-level C programming API.
That's available on Mac, Linux, Windows and on the iPhone.
The next level up is core foundation
CFNetServices and the highest layer is NSNetServices
which is the foundation layers used by Cocoa.
And for most of you in this room doing iOS development,
you'll probably be working at the NSNetServices layer
but they are all available on the iPhone.
So if you got existing code, you can still use that.
So Bonjour started off as replacing the AppleTalk
Chooser to define what's on the local network.
But when you use the Bonjour APIs
you get a lot more than that.
I've talked about discovering local things.
I've talked about discovering remote
things by Back to My Mac.
I'm going to tell you about discovering
devices that may be asleep.
This is the new feature we introduced with
Snow Leopard, we talked about last year.
I'll give a little recap of that now.
And we keep inventing new communication technologies
and they come along with their own sets of APIs
and their own addressing syntax and their own model for how
they work and that can be a burden for developers to have
to keep supporting whatever the new thing is.
So one of the great things I was
very excited about last year
with iPhone OS 3 is peer-to-peer Bonjour over Bluetooth.
So you don't have to pair Bluetooth.
You don't have to configure it.
You don't have to set up the Bluetooth
panel, configure the IP addresses.
You just use the Bonjour APIs and when you're resolved,
we will actually bring up an IP network over Bluetooth
on demand and then connect you to the other device.
And this is what's used by the Game Kit on iPhone.
But it's actually implemented as a Bonjour function
so all of your Bonjour apps get this for free as well.
So let's talk about the sleeping case.
Suppose I've got a USB printer plugged
into my Mac with printer sharing
and this is great because I can print remotely.
I can be sitting on the sofa with my laptop and I can print.
But not if the computer is asleep.
Back to My Mac, similar story.
I can get to my computer remotely but not if it's asleep.
Apple TV can access music and movies and photos of my
iTunes music collection on my iMac but not if it's asleep.
So on the one hand, customers want to put their machines to
sleep so they're not wasting energy but on the other hand,
we keep providing useful services to them that mean
they want to keep the machine awake and we wanted
to resolve this tension and make it so that you can have
the best of both worlds and that's the Bonjour Sleep Proxy.
The Bonjour Sleep Proxy runs on AirPort Base Stations.
It runs on Apple TV because that's the device that's always
on, on your network and doesn't take very much power.
If you're running internet sharing on your
Mac, then that will also act as a sleep proxy.
Basically, any device that doesn't take much power
that's always on is a great candidate for a sleep proxy.
It's open source so anybody can make
these but for most of you in the room,
I'm guessing your AirPort Base
Station is going to be your proxy.
When the Mac goes to sleep, it takes its Bonjour
service records and ships them in a packet to the proxy.
Because those service records are a compact
representation of its role on the network, what its name is,
what its address is, what services it offers, what
ports it's listening on, it takes all that information
and ships it to the proxy and says this is me, I'm
going to sleep now, wake me up if anybody wants me.
The iMac goes to sleep and the proxy sends out some proxy
out packets to say, I am now temporarily responsible
for this IP address because I'm
proxying for the device that's asleep.
Now on my other machine, I have
a document that I want to print.
So it looks up the address and port, find the Bonjour result
and it opens a TCP connection and
that TCP SYN goes to the proxy.
Because the proxy is currently the owner of that IP address.
The proxy inspects that packet and decides that this is
something that warrants waking up the sleeping machine.
So it sends a wake-up-packet and the machine wakes up.
It reclaims its IP address, TCP in the normal course
of operation will retransmit the packet which now goes
to the newly awakened machine and
the document successfully prints.
Many of you may have had this happen
without even realizing it
because like all good networking technologies,
it's frequently completely invisible.
You notice it when it fails.
If you hit command-P and the document doesn't print
and you kind of curse, oh my, My Mac has gone to sleep,
let me get up and wake it up, then you notice it.
But if you hit Print and the page comes out, you may
never have even realized that your machine was asleep.
It woke up to print the document
and then it went back to sleep.
And this is really rewarding when
networking technology works that well.
It can also be a little bit disappointing
that we're doing all this work
to make this magic work and nobody even notices.
[ Laughter ]
So it's printed the document, my machine goes back to sleep.
That was in the case where the client already knows about
the printer because I've set it up as my default printer
but because of Bonjour service advertising, a friend
could come and visit my house with a laptop computer
and they've never been on my network before.
They've never used my printer before but when they do
Bonjour browsing operation, the proxy responds on behalf
of the sleeping machine saying there's a
printing service on this network and it does
that without even having to wake the machine.
So unlike other Wake-on-LAN technologies
that have been around for a few years,
you don't need manual setup in advance to configure this.
You can walk into a network you've never been on before and
still discover services even on machines that are asleep.
[ Pause ]
Bonjour sleep proxy works with any
application that uses the Bonjour APIs.
So we use it for printer sharing.
We use it for Apple TV accessing iTunes.
Even outside the house, if you want to get
back to your Mac at home and the Mac's asleep,
the base station will wake it up
when an incoming connection comes in.
With command-line ssh, this is not something that
normal users use but the developers tend to love this.
You can be logged in to a machine with ssh and when you're
finished doing what you're doing, type pmset sleepnow
and the machine will go to sleep
without losing your TCP connection.
Sometime later, you type in that window,
first keystroke, the machine wakes back up,
does what you want, put it back to sleep again.
You can keep your connection open for days or weeks at
a time to a machine that will sleep and wake on demand
and it doesn't have to awake consuming power 24 hours a
day bust because you've got an ssh log into that machine.
And for all of your applications that advertise
services with Bonjour, if you advertise your service,
we can transfer that data to the sleep proxy.
If you don't advertise the service, we don't know
about you and we can't tell the proxy about you.
So with that, I'd like to invite Rory McGuire to
come up on stage and tell you some specific details
about Bonjour and multitasking in iPhone OS.
[ Applause ]
>> Rory McGuire: Thank you Stuart.
My name is Rory and I'm here to help
you learn about Bonjour on iPhone OS.
Specifically, we're going to go over three things.
First is peer-to-peer networking, something
that Stuart talked about a little bit.
I'll go into a little bit more detail.
The second is a new API in iOS 4
called DNSServiceSetDispatchQueue.
It's in our low-level C API and it allows
you to use GCD queues with Bonjour.
It'll make things a lot easier for you, I'll get into that.
And the new hotness for iOS 4 multitasking and what
that means for Bonjour and networking in general.
Let's get to it.
Peer-to-peer, this is something that we
introduced last year with iPhone OS 3.
You may know this as being used by Game Kit.
Well, what does it actually do?
I'm sure we're all familiar with this Wi-Fi
selection UI, Wi-Fi network selection UI.
Which network do I pick, right?
Let's say for example that you're in a room with 576 MiFis.
If I wanna use my game or use my service,
which one of these things do I pick?
Well, we're going to solve that with no configuration.
How are we going to do it?
Bluetooth.
But wait a second.
This is the Bonjour session, what
are we doing talking about Bluetooth?
Well it's Bonjour over Bluetooth.
Again, like Stuart said, there's no manual pairing.
Bonjour will automatically make the
devices connect when you do a resolve.
Again, this is used by Game Kit but
it's not required that you use Game Kit.
You only really have to use the Bonjour APIs.
So if you already have the Bonjour APIs in your
app, you will get the Bluetooth stuff for free.
How is it the same?
Exactly the same APIs, NSNetService APIs,
CFNetService APIs and the dns_sd low-level C API.
Your code will just work.
How was it different?
Well, Stuart talked a little bit about how Bonjour
actually separates browsing from resolving.
This really worked well for us
to implement this over Bluetooth.
Resolves may take a little bit longer because that's what
actually tells Bonjour to bring up the IP connection,
the PAN connection between the two devices.
So one of the things that you're going to want
to is make sure you use ResolveWithTimeout.0.
It's going to take a little bit longer
than a connection, a resolve over Wi-Fi.
Let the user decide when they've waited
long enough for this thing to come up.
That's about it.
So, let's go to little more detail about
the separation between browse and resolve.
Browsing gets you a little bit of
information about a lot of service instances.
It gets you the name of lots and lots of service instances.
Resolve on the other hand gets you a little bit of info or
gets a lot of information about one particular instance.
And in the case of Bonjour over Bluetooth, it
also brings up the Bluetooth PAN connection
which is kind of a heavyweight operation.
What you don't want to do is resolve every single service
that you find in the browse because that's going to fill
in the whole table and it's going to be very costly.
Don't browse continuously because that also
has some power and performance implications.
Don't resolve every service.
You can get a little bit more information about
the services by querying for the TXT record.
There are APIs at the NS and CF layer to get the
TXT record for the services that your browses return
so you can display a little bit
more information to the user.
But let your user decide which
service they want to connect to.
Don't just go off connecting to every single service because
you're going to be telling Bluetooth to go off and connect
to these different PAN connections if
the thing was discovered over Bluetooth.
You don't want your app to be known as
the one that drains the user's battery.
Not to be outdone, the Wi-Fi guys are actually
working on something called Wi-Fi Direct.
This is currently scheduled to have Bonjour in it.
Alright, it does some exchange with these people
to actually have this work as well using Bonjour.
What that's going to mean for you is
that you'll just use the Bonjour APIs.
Just like over Bluetooth, it's just going to work.
But of course, it's not out yet.
Next topic, DNSServiceSetDispatchQueue.
This a new API in iOS 4 and it's actually quite nice.
It's very, very simple.
You have a DNSServiceRef and you tell it,
this is the queue I want to put it on.
Before this API, when you use the
low-level C APIs for Bonjour,
you would have to create a CF socket
run loop source or you would have
to have your own kqueue loop or your own select loop.
You'd have to call DNSServiceProcessResult
or all these things you had to do
in order to get it to work with the C API.
Now, however, it's going to be just one line of code, right?
You start up your browse like you did previously,
but now instead of creating and putting something
in your select loop and calling
DNSServiceProcessResult or creating a CFRunLoop source,
all you have to do is call the SetDispatchQueue with
your DNSServiceRef and the queue you want to put it on.
In most cases, it's going to be the main queue.
Now if you're new to iPhone development or
actually you're just new to iPhone OS 4, to iOS 4,
GCD is seriously the coolest thing since sliced bread.
I love GCD.
There is the GCD on iOS session immediately
following this one in Russian Hill.
I invite everybody to attend that, please.
That's it for that API.
It's really simple.
Now on to the new hotness, multitasking.
So we're going to go through a timeline here.
What happens when your-- a standard multitask in your app.
Now, there's some other kinds of apps you can be.
You can be a VoIP app.
You can do some things with locations, things like that.
I'm not going to cover those.
Those are covered by the multitasking sessions.
I'm going to talk about general networking
in applications that are not VoIP
and not doing audio streaming and things like that.
The first thing that's going to happen when the
user hits the Home button is that you're going
to get the applicationDidEnterBackground
callback on you application delegate.
At some point after that, your
code is going to stop running.
Now, you can request a task completion and
that'll extent the amount of time that you get
to run but not really all that much, right.
At some point, your app is going to be
not be scheduled anymore by the kernel.
There is no indication when your
application actually stops running.
The only indication that you get is that
your application did enter the background.
Some point after your application stops running,
your Bonjour operations may be canceled.
In order for us to do very efficient and effective
multitasking, the system is going to reclaim resources.
Not necessarily always but it does this
so that the other applications that are
in the foreground can actually get a much better experience.
The other thing it may do is reclaim
the actual networking sockets.
Now, it's not actually going to close your sockets.
It's going to do something much more akin to a
shutdown and you don't know it's happening, right.
Your application is not actually running right now.
You're not scheduled on the processor so you have no
idea that this is going on and that this happened.
And again, it doesn't always happen.
This is when the system decides to reclaim some resources.
So at some point in the future here, your
code is actually going to resume running.
But again, you don't really get any
kind of notification this is happening.
You're just going to get scheduled again
and your code's going to start running.
What's important to note here is this is when you should
deal with the aftermath of these things happening, right.
This is where you need to be robust to errors on your
networking sockets, errors in you Bonjour operations,
all these things, because this may actually happen depending
on scheduling before you get applicationWillEnterForeground.
Do not use applicationWillEnterForeground as a
notification that you need to clean up your world.
Your world may be dirty before that because
your application actually started running
on the processor before you got this callback.
Now, in general you should be robust
to network issues, right?
This is not just multitasking.
I can walk across the room and now I'm closer to this set
of MiFis so my networking is going to be busted, right.
So just the usual walking around
might have effects on networking.
So be robust to networking issues, right including things
that happen when you get resumed after multitasking,
after going in the background and coming back up.
So merely building with iOS 4 gets you this behavior, right?
Your application will go into the
background, it will get suspended.
After a resume, all your Bonjour
networking may be broken for your app.
You'll no longer be advertising anything.
You'll no longer be discovering anything.
Your network sockets might be closed.
Detect and fix that broken state or the user experience with
your app is going to be worse than it was with iPhone OS 3.
This is very, very important, right?
There's no UI for users to go exit your app, at least
no UI that they're really going to understand, right.
There's no Quit button.
There's nothing that says I want
you to relaunch my app from scratch.
If your app doesn't clean up the first time it
resumes, your app is going to be dead in the water.
When the user switches back to your app at anytime
in the future, you don't want it to be host, right.
You want it to work again.
So be robust to these kinds of errors
even if you're not getting a resume.
You might get networking errors for other reasons.
So if you're using the NSNetService or the CFNetService
APIs, you'll get called back with an error code.
When you get callback with that error code, restart
your Bonjour operations if that's where you are,
if that's where you want your user to be.
Again, you shouldn't be browsing all the time.
You should be browsing or resolving
when the user actually wants
to because there are some power
implications and things like that.
With the lower-level C APIs, if you're
calling DNSServiceProcessResult yourself,
check for the return code ServiceNotRunning
and then restart your Bonjour operations.
If you're using the new SetDispatchQueue, it will
call all your callbacks with ServiceNotRunning
because again you're not calling
DNSServiceProcessResult yourself.
You're letting all the cool dispatch
stuff take care of that for you.
When you get ServiceNotRunning,
restart all your Bonjour operations.
If you're using the low-level C APIs, we highly
recommend that you use the new SetDispatchQueue API
because it allows for us to do future improvements, right?
In the future, we could automatically
start all the things back up for you
and you will not even get errors when you resume.
And the last thing is you can actually opt out of
this behavior by adding this thing to your info.plist.
And now back to Stuart.
[ Applause ]
>> Stuart Cheshire: Thank you Rory.
So, in other news we just released Bonjour for Windows
2.0.2 and this brings Bonjour on Windows to feature parity
with Bonjour on Mac OS 10.6, Snow Leopard.
It's installed with iTunes on Windows, with Safari.
Now with Bonjour Print Services which lets
Windows machines share printers on your Mac.
There's an SDK for developers which gives you
additional tools and the header files, the documentation.
One of the key new things which you will be happy
about if you're a Windows developer is
we have the new shared connection mode.
And I'll talk in a minute about why that's useful.
We have some stuff code to do weak-linking.
I'll explain that.
And it also supports Sleep Proxy just like Snow Leopard.
You might ask why does Apple do Bonjour for Windows?
Well, we want a world where network
products talk to each other effortlessly.
And a lot of you guys are making applications for the iPhone
and a lot of those applications may want to synchronize data
with information on the user's home computer.
And we don't want you to have to do one set of
things for Macs and something different for Windows.
So, you can use the same network protocol, a very
efficient, mature, robust service discovery protocol
and have that available on Windows as well.
On Mac OS X, adding event source to your run
loop is very easy and every Bonjour operation
in the original API stands alone as its own event source.
The feedback we have from Windows programmers
is that it's not so easy on Windows.
The way you typically program on Windows is you make the
list of sources you're waiting for then you tell Windows
to wait for something interesting
to happen with one of those sources
and then when it returns you process the events.
But having-- creating a new operation while
you're waiting means you've got to break out of
that loop and make a new list and go back into it.
And it's possible to do.
Many people have done it but it is extra work.
So, we have this new mode which is also available on Snow
Leopard and iOS which is where you make a shared connection
and then you can add new Bonjour operations
to that one shared connection which means
on application startup you make a single Windows events
source, put that in your WaitForMultipleObjects list
and then you don't have to keep
adding and removing event sources.
The way that works is first you call createConnection
on startup and then you copy that DNSServiceRef
and do a new operation passing the shared connection flag.
You can make another copy of that
service ref and start another operation.
Each operation can have a different callback
function to handle the events or as in this case,
they both have the same reply function
but they have a different context pointer
which is how the reply function knows which particular
event has just happened relating to which operation.
Typically, this context pointer would
be a pointer to your object or structure
or something else defining the state
of that operation you're doing.
I always like to show things at the developer conference
which are not made by Apple because this is an open standard
and I'm always interested to see what
the other developers are doing with it.
RealVNC is now using Bonjour in
their Windows and iPad products.
I am going to show you that.
Their server for Windows advertises with Bonjour and
their client on the iPad uses Bonjour to discover servers.
RealVNC is using the weak-linking
capability that I talked about.
On the Mac, since the day before OS X,
we had this concept called weak-linking.
You could write an app that linked to some feature
that was new in Mac OS 10.6 and if the user ran it
on 10.5 they wouldn't get a DLL link error.
The application would still launch but its functions
would be effectively like null function pointers.
And you as a developer could know that and check
those functions were not null before you called them
and that way your application would still run.
It just might miss some of the new functionality
but it's not going to fail to launch.
It came as a surprise to us that Windows doesn't have that.
So, that means developers have to roll their own
functionality and again this was feedback we heard
from developers and in Bonjour for
Windows 2.0, we do that for you.
We have helpers to help you link in your library and
it does the DLL calls to see if Bonjour is installed
and if it's not installed then when you call the function
you get an error and so it uses that so you don't have
to have Bonjour installed to use their
server and if it's not installed,
their server will try to advertise the service and
get an error and it will continue and run correctly.
But if Bonjour is installed then
the server will advertise with it.
So let's see if I can show you that now.
Okay, so, I have my machine here
running Windows and I have my iPad.
I will-- this is the RealVNC VNCViewer and I can run
this and this is the out of the box configuration.
Let's see what's available on the network.
And without typing in any configuration information,
this has used Bonjour to find a
couple of VNC servers it can talk to.
This version displays the IP address.
You wouldn't do that in a normal application but one
thing you will notice here is those addresses say 169.254
and I'm pointing that out because I'm
not connected to any of the network here.
This is just on my laptop here.
I created a wireless network and on the iPad I joined it.
There is no DXUP server.
This is a TCP/IP network with 2 devices on it.
They pick their own link local
addresses, they use Multicast DNS.
They've discovered each other and this is a common developer
mistake to say wait, I better use the reachability APIs
and make sure I can talk to the internet and oh no, I can't.
I'm going to put up an error messages and refuse to work.
You don't need to talk to the great
mainframe in the sky to do useful networking.
Quite often you may have a device
that you just want to set up
and VNC could be a great way of
doing that and talking to that.
The reachability APIs are a great way to notify you.
If you try to connect and you fail, you
can use reachability to get a notification
about when the network environment has changed.
So it might be good time to try again.
But there are terrible preflight checks
because they can only ever make things worse.
If you just try to connect you will either succeed or fail.
If you use reachability as a preflight check before
that it can't ever make a failed connection succeed.
A connection that would have failed will still fail but it
can make you not try in a case that would have succeeded.
So general lesson here and I highly recommend going
to the sessions this afternoon at
networking on iPhone OS, two parts.
They cover a lot of details about dealing with networking in
a modern world, particularly networking on mobile devices.
I recommend those.
And let's see what happens when I connect to this.
And so, with zero-configuration I have just
discovered and connected from an Apple iPad device
to a Microsoft Windows machine
and you saw how easy that was.
For any of you guys who've set up things like network
cameras and tried to configure IP address and things.
You know it can be something that you
planned half a Saturday afternoon for.
With Bonjour you just connect and
it works, so let's move on.
[ Applause ]
So I have-- this is not a shipping
product yet but I'm very excited.
Oh I'm sorry, I'm getting ahead.
So, you all know that the iPhone uses
WebKit as its HTML rendering engine.
And I'm sure you know that Palm devices
and Android phones use WebKit as well.
And you know that iPhone OS uses
Bonjour for its service discovery.
Well I'm very happy to say that last month at
Palm's developers conference they announced
that Palm will also be supporting the Bonjour APIs
and you can already get Android apps that use Bonjour
by embedding a Java implementation of
Bonjour but by the end of the year,
I'm told that Android OS will have Bonjour APIs itself
so that every app doesn't have to embed its own copy.
So, you could use the same HTML
5 on all these mobile platforms
and you can use the same Bonjour service
discovery on all these mobile platforms.
Now I'm sure many people in this room have probably
experimented with the technology called X10.
For those of you who don't know, it's a power line signaling
mechanism that's been around since the '70s, I think.
And the idea is great.
You can have a little module that you plug into
the wall and you plug your table lamp into it.
And then you could have another device, a switch connected
to the power lines that's not mechanically
switching the power on and off.
It's sending signals over the power line to tell that
module to turn the lights on or off or brighten or dim.
And this is a great idea for being more flexible
about how you control things in your house.
But the protocol is slow and unreliable.
There's no acknowledgment.
There's no retransmission.
So, for a lot of people it's a very frustrating experience.
The promise is there but the reality
doesn't really live up to it.
And time is long overdue I think for something
that is like X10 but works a lot better.
These products and they are not on sale yet
so I'm not going to give the company name
but look for these in the shops by Christmas, I hope.
This is little module you plug in the power outlet and they
have Wi-Fi in them and Bonjour and there's an iPhone app
which uses Bonjour to discover all of these modules
wirelessly, not over the power line over Wi-Fi.
And from the iPhone app you can tell it to turn
on or off or brighten or dim but the difference
because this is Wi-Fi is you don't press brighten
4 times and two of the packets got lost so you have
to press a few more times to reach the right brightness.
That kind of worked when a human is doing it
but when a computer is controlling things,
it can't tell how bright the light is by looking
at it so you really need something reliable.
So, you can send commands to the module to
turn on and turn off and brighten and dim.
That circle on the front is actually
a push button so you can override it.
So, if you don't want to dig out your phone
you can press the button to turn it on and off.
And because it's all software controlled when you press
that button, it can signal back to the app on your iPhone
or your computer that the button was
pushed which you can use as a trigger
to turn other things on or off in the house.
These things also have a power meter in them.
Some of the people in this room have probably
bought power meters because they are curious
about how much power their television and
their computer and their printer take.
Well, these have power metering built into them.
So you don't need a separate box with an LCD display.
Just on your iPhone screen, you can see the amount
of power that's being consumed by each device plugged
into these things and even chart it overtime to
see the refrigerator compressor cycling on and off.
And you can use that as a trigger for
events so that when you turn the television
on it senses the increased power draw and sends messages
to other modules to tell them to turn off the lights
and turn on the amplifier and you can build all
of these things that communicate with each other
and automate things in your home over Wi-Fi using Bonjour.
So, the whole Bonjour team is very excited
about this and we're going to be first
in line to buy these as soon as they go on sale.
This was exactly the kind of thing that I hoped to see
happen when we started the Bonjour effort ten years ago.
Bonjour is not just about desktop Macs and PCs, although
it's certainly good that we make those easier to use
but where it's critically important is
devices like this where you can't hook
up a screen and a keyboard to configure them.
They absolutely have to be bullet proof and self
configuring and you can't afford the tech support costs
of people calling up trying to
work at how to configure them.
You have to just have them plug in and work.
So with that, I'll get to our tips and reminders.
You've heard this in other sessions
and I'm going to repeat it here.
Make sure your applications work with IPv6.
IPv4 has link-local addressing but it was
kind of an add-on after the fact to IPv4.
IPv6 has had it built-in from the start
and the API supports it more elegantly.
So, we wholeheartedly recommend IPv6.
We use IPv6 in our own base stations,
that's how you configure AirPort Express is
with an IPv6 link-local address to communicate with it.
You'll hear this message in the iPhone networking sessions.
Networking is asynchronous.
Things don't always in the real world
like they might work in your lab.
Here's one example.
If you do asynchronous blocking DNS call on your main
thread and the DNS server happens to be not responsive
for that user, the standard DNS time matches 30 seconds.
Well, your app will get jettisoned
after 20 seconds if it's not responsive.
So, your app dies.
People say why don't you just make the timeout shorter?
But that really isn't the answer because
even having your app unresponsive
for 5 seconds is not a good user experience for the user.
And 5 seconds may not be long enough for a slow DNS server.
So, the answer is not synchronous blocking
calls and trying to get the time out right.
The answer is to embrace the fact
that networking is asynchronous.
Do things on a background thread or even better,
do things in an event driven basis using CFRunLoop
or using the new libdispatch Grand Central Scheduling.
Some that we see sometimes in Windows applications
is a Refresh button and we don't want to see
that in Bonjour applications on Mac or Windows and
if you think about the iChat Bonjour Buddy List think
about the sidebar on iTunes, think about the
Safari Bonjour list, there's no Refresh button.
The list should always be fresh.
So, the Bonjour APIs make this very easy.
You start to browse you get out and remove
events for the lifetime of that browse.
You don't have to have a timer the way you do when
you browse every minute to see what's changed.
We've seen applications that do a browse for 10
seconds and then stop and then another one and then--
That's actually harder on the network than just leaving
the browse running because the browse settles off
to a low query rate and then just pays
attention to the events on the network.
Generally, we recommend using the window so when the user
wants to connect to a service you may have a UI today
where there's a field where they type in the host name.
Well, you can still have that but next to that you can
have a Bonjour button which brings up a browsing list.
And for the time that list is on
the screen it should be live.
And then the user closes it and you stop the browse.
We prefer a window to a pull down menu because while the
APIs exist from modifying a pull down menu while it's
on the screen, it's disconcerting to use this.
They're not really used to pulling down a menu and
seeing all the things jumble around and change.
So we recommend using a window not a pull down menu.
The way your client will discover instances of your service
and not other services is that
every service has a unique name.
You don't have to pay to register this.
Just go to dns-sd.org and make sure you
register a unique identifier for your service.
We often see in the wild on networks like WWDC here,
we look at the services that are being advertised
and we always see a few that aren't
on the service type list.
So, save yourself headaches by just going to that
webpage, send the email, register your service type.
In the first version of Bonjour many
years ago we had a domain parameter.
And it was there for future expansion
but it wasn't used at the time.
Now, that we have wide area Bonjour and Back
to My Mac, don't ignore the domain parameter.
When you do a browse you get back name, type, domain, and
the interface index and you need to store all of those
or at least name, type, and domain and pass
those three unchanged to the resolve call.
We have seen bugs where people ignore the domain or they
just hard code local and that works with local Bonjour
but you're losing the benefits
of Back to My Mac if you do that.
Don't ignore the port number.
Historically, networking has had
the concept of well-known ports.
Port80 is the web server.
Well, you can only have one port80 on a machine.
So with fast user switching, if there's
multiple application and multiple copies
of the same application running they
can't all have the same port number.
There are a lot of bits to software today
that use a webpage as their configuration UI
which is great but again, they can't all have port80.
When you've got multiple computers at home behind
the NAT Gateway, they're all sharing one IP address.
There's only one port80 on that IP address.
So, we knew this was going to happen and that's why the
Bonjour resolve call gives you back the port number.
When you create your service, you can specify 0 when you
bind and the kernel will pick an unused port for you.
The register API has a parameter for you to say
what port number you're listening on and that goes
into the network packets and the resolve call
will tell the clients we have seen applications.
They do the resolve.
They get back the address in the port.
They ignore the port and try to connect to the
well-known ports and that only works if you get lucky.
The first copy of the application may get
the port at once but all the others won't.
So, this creates situations with Back to My Mac or with
other wide area Bonjour things where you can only connect
to one thing at the group but the other ones that aren't
on the standard port don't work when
they connect to the wrong thing.
For your marketing materials and
your packaging and your webpages,
if you use Bonjour then you can license the Bonjour
logo for no cost just like the Made for iPhone
and Made for iPad logos to let your customers
know that they can expect a painless,
trouble-fee experience with your products.
If you're using the Bonjour APIs on Mac
and Windows then you are good to go.
If you are building pieces of hardware which we love to see
then we have a Bonjour conformance test which you can run
to help you find bugs in your implementation and if you pass
that test then you can also use
the Bonjour logo on your packaging.
And I encourage you to run that test
because it does help you find bugs
that might cause trouble for customers in the field.
If you are doing something where you want a component
that runs on Windows you can license Bonjour for Windows
and that is also free with iTunes being on so many machines.
There are a hundred million copies of Bonjour for Windows
already out there so you may not even have to install it
but if you want to include that with your
software you can license that for no fee.
Safari on Windows has the same Bonjour
browsing that Safari on Mac OS X does.
So to wrap up, especially with things like
peer-to-peer over Bluetooth on the phone,
having an app that's constantly browsing all the
time in the background has a toll in battery life.
So, when the user hits the button to bring up your browsing
list you start the browse and then leave the browse live
so they're getting live information
but when the user dismisses, it stops.
That's what we recommend.
We know that not all apps from
Apple set the best example here.
iTunes has the sidebar that's browsing all
the time but particularly on the phone,
we recommend browsing when the user
is actually actively looking for stuff
but otherwise, don't be browsing all the time.
And in the same vein, don't resolve everything
you find because that could be very expensive.
You're triggering a whole bunch of mechanism by
resolving there that you really don't need to trigger
until you're actually ready to make a connection.
Embrace the fact that networking is asynchronous.
It can seem like a pain if you're used to non-network
programming where the computer is in charge
where you say do this and then do this and then do this
and you'll write nice sequential
programs the way we all learn to program.
But networking like graphical user interfaces
is one area where you are not in charge.
In GUIs, the user is deciding what
button to click next and in networking,
the environment around you is deciding
what's going to happen next.
And fighting against that is really unproductive.
Pay attention to the multitasking
issues that Rory told you about.
You have to pay attention to the network sockets
being broken because otherwise when your app resumes,
it may not work and with no easy way for the user to quit
it, we don't want to be in a situation where users end
up rebooting their phone because they don't know
how to fix the broken apps and use the Bonjour logo.
This is the contact information
for our technology evangelists.
We have documentation on the webpage.
In the interest of full disclosure,
I was co-author on this book.
This is the O'Reilly Zero Configuration
Networking book which is a--
I'd like to say it's a more cohesive form of documentation
in the sense that you can read it safely in the bathtub.
Later today we have the iPhone OS networking sessions
which I highly recommend, the Core OS Networking overview,
you can watch on video and the Multitasking on
iPhone OS is going to be repeated on Friday.