>> John Wright: Hello, everyone.
My name is John Wright.
I'm part of Platform Technologies in Core OS.
We're responsible for a lot of the
security infrastructure in iOS.
And today, we're going to talk about-- a
little bit about protecting data on the phone.
So we're going to go over-- this is our agenda.
So first, I'm going to talk a little bit about what data
protection is and what security mechanisms we have in place
in iOS and kind of how they've
evolved over the different releases.
And then we're going to kind of do a deep dive
into the design of our data protection mechanisms,
and this is more for your security analysis.
This is not something that you actually need to know.
It's all done under the covers.
But I think a lot of you that are kind of in the
trust-but-verify hats, really want to know this information.
Then we're going to talk a little bit about enabling
data protection, both from a user standpoint
and from an enterprised standpoint of managing a device.
And then we're going to talk a
little bit about the API's that you--
that we want you to adopt in your applications to be
in data protection and how to protect your user's data.
So these devices that we have, these phones and iPads
and iPod touches, they're very personal devices,
and they have a lot of-- more data on them than we've
ever had before ringing around people's pockets.
And one of the things that is kind of
a challenge here is that them being
so mobile also means they're more easily stolen by someone.
And you have a lot of different data on here.
You have all your messages from your messaging systems,
you have your accounts for those social networks,
you might have accounts for financial information,
and you might have even enterprised apps
that you're actually responsible for
protecting your company's information.
So this has become very, very important, being able to
protect this data, especially in a mobile environment.
So what we introduced last year on iPhone
3GS was all the data was encrypted in place.
Now, we actually added special hardware to these
devices that would have no performance impact.
Basically, it's you know, hardware encryption
engines in the hardware that would do it
for no performance, no battery life impact whatsoever.
Now, the big reason that we did this was we
want a really fast experience of Remote Wiping.
So Remote Wipe is that you can send a signal to
the phone as long as that phone is still online
that it will erase all that customer's data.
So you can do this from, you know, if the device is lost.
And we wanted that to be very, very fast.
And if you encrypt all the data, you can
just throw away the keys, makes it very fast.
Now, it also has this concept of
protecting the data at rest.
Now, this is kind of a concept that evolved from desktops.
And the idea on desktops is that a lot of desktops, you
can image your data and move it to somewhere else to try
to compromise, or someone can steal a hard drive out of it.
Now, this doesn't really apply
to a lot of these mobile devices.
So it makes-- if you have that device, it makes
that device still very vulnerable to a local attack.
Now, the other thing that we added
last year was encrypted backups.
And this means that the data is protected when it is
off the device and being backed up to a host machine.
So what we're introducing for iOS 4.
We have this goal to keep the data
safe even if the device is compromised.
So what we did is we added the ability to tie
the encrypted data to the user's passcode.
So this means that it's actually something that
the user knows themselves that unlocks that data,
so that data is only available when the device is unlocked.
Now, we added API's in so you can choose data
availability, whether it's only available
when the device is unlocked, or it's available all the time.
And we went about adopting this in iOS 4 in
mail, which is by far, the most complicated app
and does the most complicated background activity.
And we're making those API's available for you to adopt in
your apps, so you can tie into the same security mechanism.
And I want to emphasize here again, there's absolutely no
performance impact to this because we're doing this all
in the hardware engine itself,
and it's all just streamlining
with how the data reads and writes out of the hardware.
Now, I also want to mention that we
still had to enable encrypted backups,
and we actually had retool all
of our infrastructure to do this.
But we got one big benefit.
We now can allow the key chain to be migrated
between devices if they are in an encrypted backup.
So this was kind the last kind of excuse not to use
the Keychain is that your credentials wouldn't move
from device to device when your users upgrade.
Well, now they do.
In an encrypted back-up scheme, they just move right across.
So passcodes, we are tying this to the passcodes.
But I want to remind everyone that the passcode
is only as good as you make the passcode.
And passcodes can be pretty forced.
So if you choose one, two, three, four as
your passcode, it's not gonna be very strong.
Someone is going to guess that.
So we put a bunch of mitigations in place.
Now, the first mitigation that we've always had in
place is that we have back off between failed attempts
on using the UI to putting someone's passcode.
So it's kind of incremental as you have failed attempts.
But by the sixth failed attempt, it takes
like, 10 minutes for the UI to come back up
and offer to you to put your passcode here.
So this makes, you know, someone who's
stolen your device, if they are just trying
to punch the numbers it makes it
pretty difficult for them to guess.
It takes them a long time.
Now, we've also had the ability to
force complex passcodes on the device.
We've had this for a while with configuration profiles.
Now, what's new for iOS 4 is we actually give
you a user-configurable setting in the settings--
on the settings tab to actually force the
complex-- or to actually use a complex passcode.
Also, we've had the ability to force
and erase of all the user's data
after a failed numbers of attempts at the passcode.
This is also something in iOS 4 that
we've made user-configurable in settings.
Now, another thing that we did in tying
all the data to the passcode is we, not--
didn't just tie it to the passcode itself, we also
tied it into a set of device keys in the hardware.
And the reason that we did this is that it makes it--
it prevents people from taking the data off the device
and trying to brute force passcodes
there, since it's actually encrypted also
with a key that's only available in the hardware.
That means that you actually have to-- someone would
actually have to do an attack on that hardware itself.
And our hardware is fast, but it's not as fast as a botnet.
So this actually limits the speed
of an attack on these passcodes.
So I want to kind of just run through
what technologies we put in iOS
and kind of why we put them there
over the generations of releases.
So obviously, we have had, since
the first iPhone, a passcode.
And this was really, you know, at that
time meant to prevent casual device access.
It was meant to stop someone, kind of, at the door
and make them know one number before
they could actually use that device.
Now, even at that point in time, we had
some Privilege Separation and Sandboxing.
And what Privilege Separation is, it means that
applications, either in the OS or third party applications,
only have access to those services
that they have privileges for.
And Sandboxing is that basically, they only have access
to those documents or API's that they have privileges for.
Now, this has kind of evolved over time because obviously,
in the first release of iOS, there was no third party apps.
And as we added third party apps, we added more
Sandboxing, we put those apps in the Sandbox.
Now, for iOS 2, we also added Code Signing.
And the reason that we did this
is that now, the user knows that--
they know that there is known origins
for every piece of code on their device.
This makes it much more difficult to spread around viruses
and the like because you can actually trace it back
to whether it's an enterprise, inhouse app, or whether it's
an app from the App Store, or whether it's code from Apple.
We also added Remote Wipe at that time.
Now this would, you know, like I said
before, erases all the data in the phone,
if that phone is still online, you can send it a signal.
And obviously, at that time, what has to
happen is we actually had to overwrite the data
with zeros essentially, to erase that data.
And then actually, it was a pretty long process,
especially for the larger storage devices.
So last year, we added encrypted storage.
The main reason for that is to
make Remote Wipe very, very fast,
and we added encrypted backups, which
protects the data off the device.
And now, we're adding data protection.
And this really means that even if a device is compromised
in some way, it's stolen and it's a compromised device,
that user's data is still protected because it's
protected with something that only that user knows.
So you can see where this is all going here.
We want all the apps to adopt data protection, both
throughout the OS and throughout all of your apps.
So we start it with Mail which is the most complex app,
and we want you to go through your app
and choose how your data is protected.
Now, the big thing here is that for app surges
in the foreground, when the device is locked
and not doing anything, it's pretty easy to choose
they want their data protected by the passcode.
If you are doing some kind of multitasking
app that has some kind of background task,
you have to be a little bit more careful with your data,
and you have to choose a few different
classes to figure out how to do that.
But we want you to start adopting these
API's and these concepts into your apps
because our real ultimate goal here is
that when the user puts on their passcode,
they know all their data is protected no matter what.
So I'd like to invite up Mitch Adler,
one of our Security Architects,
to talk a little bit about-- more
about the mechanism behind us.
[ Applause ]
>> Mitch Adler: Thanks, John.
As John said, I'm going to take you on a little deeper
dive into the mechanisms we put together in our system
to help protect the user's data with their passcode.
It-- the goal, as John said, is that when
the device is locked, the user should be able
to be confident that their device is protected.
And in iOS 3, we were relatively confident that if
I-- my device is locked and I hand it to somebody
and I watch them not penetrate the defense of
the device, they're not going to be able to get
through my passcode very easily because we limit the
tries and all of the mitigations that John talked about.
But for iOS 4, we want to provide a mechanism that the user
can be confident that even if they've lost their device,
if their passcode, if their device is
locked, that their data is actually protected
with their passcode, the strength to their passcode.
That requires that we actually encrypt their
data with some derivation of their passcode.
And this is very useful, but we run into a problem.
And that problem is that applications want to use
some of that data sometimes when the device is locked.
So we needed to provide a mechanism for applications to
specify jar system how they want given data protected.
That mechanism is data protection classes.
There are three data protection classes that
we have established in our system in our API.
The first class is available and unlocked.
That's the most protecting class.
The availability and the protection are kind of reverse
of each other, when something is available to the system
than an attacker who manages to
get through our outer protections
and get inside the system can masquerade
as an application and access that data.
So if you set your data be able-- if you
set your protection class to one that to--
WhenUnlocked, we'll protect the data
cryptographically when the system is locked,
and we'll make it available to your app when it's unlocked.
The second class is available after fist unlock.
This is the kind of compromise class.
We noted that many of the attacks on the device that
compromise devices and get access to running code
on the device requires the device reboot.
In the process of rebooting, we can
reset things that have been exposed.
So we add the second class, so that if there is data that
you need to continue accessing while the device is locked,
for example, credentials to reconnect to your server because
you've changed networks and now you need to reconnect
and revalidate, you can protect those credentials
better than not at all, but still have them available
when the device locks and unlocks, because after
the first unlock, it will be available for you.
And then if somebody attacks the device and then
forces it to reboot, we'll reprotect that data.
The last availability class is what we've
had traditionally on all of our storage
up to this date, which is it's available always.
It is no less protected than it has been in the past,
but it doesn't gain anything from data protection.
But it's a way to express that need, if I
need my data to be exactly the same as it is.
So the two major clients of these classes that present
them to you in the file system, which presents availability
for WhenUnlock called ProtectionComplete and
that available always called ProtectionNone,
under the Keychain which provides availability for
all three, WhenUnlocked, AfterFirstUnlock, and Always.
So these two clients, there is some risk that if the
two clients were sharing all of their keys and classes,
that if I were a client of one of the systems, I could
use it to attack data stored in the other system.
So for that reason, we make these very much independent.
They have very intentionally similar semantics.
So when you're thinking about how you store your data,
you can think about the problem
the same way for the two systems.
But from the point of view of how the data is
protected, we use completely separate class keys
to represent those classes, so we can isolate--
the people can access the Keychain from the people
who are allowed to access the data on the file system.
I'm going to run through a quick example to
demonstrate how we take some data that the user has
and protect it through our new design system in iOS 4.
So here's an example of a file, a mail that I happen
to compose on the device, and it needs to be protected.
In iOS 4, every file in the file system or
how it's made is protected with a file key.
This is slightly different than it was in iOS 3 and
that the whole file system is protected by a key.
But in iOS 4, there's a randomly generated
new key for every file that gets created.
That file key is stored in the files metadata.
That file key is, in turn, protected by a class key.
This is a class-- a key that was randomly generated
at the time the class was established,
and it protects the file key.
If you don't have the class key, can't see the file key.
If you don't have the file key, you
can't see the contents of the file.
Each class key is protected by an appropriate set
of keys in the system depending on its semantics.
In this particular case, this is a-- protected with the
user pin key, it's protected by two keys, the device key,
to make attacks off the device less practical,
and the user passcode key which is the tie
that ties the protection of the file back to the passcode.
The file is protected by the file key, the
file key is protected by the class key,
the class key is protected by the user passcode key.
There's one more thing that we needed
to support in this architecture,
and that was the ability to do fast Remote Wipe.
In the past we have thrown away the one
master file system key and it erased--
cryptographically erased the entire file system.
Now that we don't have exactly one master key, we had
to build one back in, and that's on all the metadata.
The file metadata has file system
key, that key, when erased,
makes it cryptographically impossible
to view the data on the file.
So to take this particular example, and show you
how we take a collection of data and protect it,
for an entire file system, we can have one
file, like we just showed you, protected,
the file protected by it's file key, the file key protected
by it's class key, and the class key protected appropriately
by a device key in our user passcode key.
But since we've gone through this class key, we can
have as many files as we'd like protected in this class.
So there's no limit, the class-- the-- each
file can specify it belongs to this class.
We also don't have to limit ourselves
to how many classes we want.
We can have a second class with exactly the same
protections and maybe some different semantics
on how you get the class key, and we can store
it on the same data storage, same file system.
We can have a third class with different semantics.
In this particular example, this would be accessed always.
There's no protection that extends from
the user passcode key to this class key.
So this is how we store on our system things that are
always available that are protected by the device key,
but they're not protected by the user passcode key.
The collection of classes that protect
data on the system, we call a keybag.
The-- that collection of class keys is an
important structure in our architecture.
It's what embodies locking, unlocking,
and protection states.
There are three kinds of keybags
we operate in our system with.
There's the System Keybag, there's a Backup
Keybag, and there's an Escrow Keybag.
The first two are relatively important
for everybody to understand.
The last one is an interesting detail for anybody
who wants to do security analysis on their device.
System keybags, these are the ones
you'd imagine, as I've just described,
they're sitting on the system,
they're protecting your system.
They hold the class keys for all
the data that's on your system.
They have one tweak they do.
They force all of the class keys, and
then to be protected with the device key
that makes it hard to attack this keybag off the device.
They're stored on the system.
They're actually stored on the file system, which
is interesting, because the fact that they're stored
in the file system means that if you use a weak
passcode that's trying to protect this keybag,
and we leave that data on the file system, somebody later
can come and find it even if we've moved on to a new keybag
and use that old keybag to try and steal your class keys.
Because when passcodes change,
we don't change the class keys.
That way, we don't have to scour the entire file
system trying to update it for this metadata.
So in order to mitigate that attack, we
actually protect the storage of the keybag
on the file system with a key that we can erase.
Every time the user changes the
passcode, we destroy the old key,
we write a new copy of the Keychain out of
the keybag out, and we write a new--
we use a new key, and we randomly generate a key.
So we've cryptographically erased the old
keybag so that it's older, maybe weaker,
passcode protection is not exposing my device anymore.
The system keybag is also responsible for
managing the lock and unlock state of the system.
When the user enters their passcode, the system keybag
is asked to expose the class keys that should be exposed
when the device unlocked, and when it's told the device is
locking, it discards those keys, forgets those class keys.
So it's-- this is the center of the universe of the device
locking and unlocking and protecting the user's data.
But in order for us to maintain our encrypted
backups and to maintain our protection
through it, we also created backup keybags.
Backup keybags are created new for every back up.
Their class keys are generated randomly and are
different for every backup you've-you storeon your host.
This holds the class keys that protects the data
while it sits in the backup on those machine.
These class keys, instead of being protected by
the pin, are protected by the backup password.
So when you have a protected backup, we-- everyone
who would have used the pin on the device are going
to be using the backup password
in the protected backup keybag.
We happened to use PBKDF2, for
those who care to generate the key.
I don't remember the number of iterations off top of my
head, happy to look it up for you if you want to know.
If you don't choose to have a backup password though, we do
one thing to protect credentials that are on the Keychain.
If you don't choose to protect your backup, we protect
some of the Keychain class keys with the device key,
and not the backup password key,
causing them not to be able to migrate,
and we'll get into that in more detail later in Adoption.
The last kind of keybag is a keybag
we created to enhance user experience.
It was created for systems to be able to hold on to.
It's called the Escrow Keybag.
It was created for other systems to
hold on to improve user experience.
The downside is that the improved user experience
we want is systems that sync with your device,
can sync without you having to
enter the passcode on your device.
And right there conceptually, is a security issue, in that
now there is data in the world that can unlock my device.
So we did a few things to mitigate it.
First, we considered that the system
that you're storing the Escrow Keybag
on is a system you're already syncing you data to.
So if somebody can compromise that system and
get your Escrow Keybag, additionally being able
to compromise your device, if they can get their hands
on your device, is not a big leap in security weakness.
It's a little-- it's irritating and annoying
but it's not of great loss, because most likely,
all of your sync data is sitting
on that host that was compromised.
Them getting your Escrow Keybag is a
potential future problem, but immediately,
they've probably already taken all of your data.
The other thing we do is that we keep a key on the
original device so we can invalidate the Escrow Keybag.
It's part of the protection.
The class keys in this keybag are protected with a device
key, so this keybag can't be brute force except with access
to the device, and the key we generated when we
made the Escrow Keybag and stored on the device.
So if we could throw that key away on the device,
we can make that Escrow Keybag cryptographically
incapable of reading the data on the device.
So anytime we decide that somebody's not worthy
of trust, we can throw away the key, of course,
part of the Escrow Keybag, and
they can't access our data anymore.
Something I didn't mention is the Escrow Keybag
does contain actual copies of the master class keys
for the devices classes, which is why it can
unlock the device without the user's passcode.
So to dive a little deeper into the filesystem
protection, all of the filesystem data is encrypted.
Everything on the filesystem.
It has been since iOS 3.
We've changed how we encrypt out the data on the filesystem.
The metadata uses the filesystem
key as I showed you in the diagram.
That's what destroyed on Remote Wipe and breaks the chain
of cryptographic exposure, so we-- your data is not exposed.
The files are encrypted to an individual
file key which is stored in the metadata.
The default, when you're creating a
new file in iOS 4, is ProtectionNone.
This is mostly for compatibility with applications,
we don't want you to break all the
applications that do anything across lock.
We want them to opt in and decide what
they-- how they want to protect it.
And again, a reminder, there's no performance impact.
We are already encrypting and decrypting.
We've just changed what keys we're using in the process
of pushing stuff back and forth to the file system.
The Keychain-- it's also protected by classes just for the
Keychain, as the concept of migratable and not migratable.
That as-- that actually doubles the number of classes that
are available for the Keychain because you can put a piece
of data into any of the three classes,
and either migratable or not migratable.
The default on the Keychain will remove
data from back to a device by iOS 4,
or if you create data without adopting data
protection, will be always as migratable.
The three new classes that aren't
migratable have the suffix ThisDeviceOnly.
So WhenUnlock, ThisDeviceOnly, WhenUnlock--
AfterFirstUnlock, ThisDeviceOnly, AlwaysThisDeviceOnly.
So this is a change that is in significance to people who
want to protect data and don't want it to move form device
to device, because our default now is going to
allow things to migrate through a protected backup.
We thought that was the right compromise
for user experience.
But if you have data that is really not supposed to migrate
off of this device ever, you'll need to update your use
to annotate that data and say it's not supposed to migrate.
Handling of the passcode.
So one of the most critical things in trying to keep
the user secret a secret is how we handle the passcode,
because we have given that secret,
and we have it for a while,
and we really don't want to keep
it because it's the user secret.
It's not our secret.
So we do two things to try and
help protect that user secret.
The first thing we do is try and make it difficult to
brute force attack the key that we derive from the passcode
to avoid simple brute forcing the-- a user's passcode.
And as John mentioned, we take a hardware key, something
that's actually embedded in hardware individual
to a given device, we do a derivation with that
hardware key which resembles PBKDF2, but isn't exactly,
and do a bunch of iterations to make you need to use
that device in order to be able to attack the passcode.
This means that an attacker whose managed to get access
to your device, broken through our outer defenses,
gotten to the point where he's got a copy of
your system keybag and wants to try to unlock it,
and knows what it should look like-- what the
header it should look like if it's unlocked,
actually has to keep trying on
that device to unlock that keybag.
This helps us be able to control
the time it takes to attack once.
For example on an iPhone 4, on a new
hardware, we use 50,000 hardware operations
to drive the key from the original passcode.
It takes about 50 milliseconds, give or take.
And if you do the math from there, for a
reasonable passcode somebody's put on the device,
it starts taking significant amounts of time,
cryptographically interesting amounts in time,
for you to brute force somebody's passcode.
The other thing we do is we handle the
passcode and the passcode key very carefully.
When we've given the passcode, and we to return it into a
passcode key, we're careful to erase remnants to make sure
that the user secrets stays the user secret.
The thing we retain when the device
unlocks, are the exposed class keys.
So when we move from state to state, class keys
come and go, and they're available and they're not.
Example of this, a device boot, we start
out-- we don't know the user's passcode,
he's never entered it, we're fresh and clean.
The only class that is available is the always class,
ProtectionNone, AlwaysThisDeviceOnly are available,
the first two protection classes
aren't available yet because we don't--
we haven't been able to unwrap the class keys.
When the user enters their passcode,
we unwrap the class keys, we--
if we get their passcode and their passcode key that help
protect the class keys, but we keep this class keys around.
So now, all of the classes are available.
WhenUnlock, AfterFirstUnlock, they're all available,
the device operates, people do their normal operations.
But at some point, the device gets
locked, either by idling to lock
or by the user clicking the lock button
and wanting the device to lock itself.
When that happens we forget the
class keys for the first class.
So that things that are only available when unlocked
are no longer available, the device is locked.
Note that the second class stays around as is defined
after FirstUnlock, it remains available until we reboot,
then we'll get back into the initial
state, we've lost all the class keys.
So in summary about our mechanism and how we put this
all together, our protection extends through a keybag,
it comes from the user's secrets and device keys
to bind it to the device and bind it to the user,
it goes to the filesystem in the Keychain
and the data stored in those places.
The passcode key derivation has been made resistant to
brute force attack to help protect the user's passcode.
And the Keychain contents have been made
migratable when we have protected backups.
And with that, I'll hand it back to John
to talk some more about configuration.
>> John Wright: Thanks, Mitch.
[ Applause ]
. So for user-enabled data protection,
actually on an iPhone 4, it's extremely simple.
The formats already there in the device.
All they have to do is set a passcode,
and data protection is enabled.
Now, on our last generation of devices, including iPhone
3GS and the iPod touch, the 3rd generation iPod touch,
it's a little bit more complicated and that we don't
have the right file system format on those devices,
and you have to upgrade the file system format.
And the way we do that is with an Erase Install.
And so, the user has to backup their device, do a
full Erase Install, and then restore from that backup.
And of course, the iPad is also capable of doing
this, and it will inherit this feature with iOS 4,
and it will also require an Erase
Install to get that feature.
Now, to check to see if Data Protection is enabled
if you go to Settings-> General-> Passcode Lock,
and there is a picture right there, if you look at
that little string at the very bottom of that screen,
it basically says Data Protection is enabled.
So now, you know you have it on that device.
Now, I want to point out a couple
of other things on this screen.
So I told you before that users now can configure their
device to be able to Wipe if-- on 10 failed passcode events.
That is that setting right there.
And they're also able to set a arbitrary complex
passcode by turning off the simple passcode,
and then the dialog that comes up to change
their passcode is a full alpha numeric keyboard,
and they can choose what size length complexity they want.
Now, for devices that are being managed and our system
to manage these devices is-- our Configuration Profiles.
You can set this Configuration Profiles
to enforce certain security requirements,
and I'd like to point a few of those out there.
So, the first one is that you can require
data protection to be enabled on that device.
You can also require a passcode be set, the link of
that passcode, and the complexity of that passcode.
You can also require a minimum passcode grace
period, and the grace period is how long a user has
from the time they turn off the screen to when they
turn on the screen again that it requires a passcode.
And you can also inquire that all the backups
from that device are encrypted backups.
Now, something else that we're introducing with
iOS 4 is a way to manage your mobile devices,
a bunch of API's actually use these
Configuration Profiles with third party servers
and third party device management systems.
And these device management systems will be capable of
doing initial device configuration and automatic updates
of these Configuration Profiles, and then also be
able to implement their own Remote Wipe capabilities.
And there was a whole session on Tuesday
that went over how these API's work.
And we've assumed that third parties will be
adopting these into their device management systems.
So that really makes a very capable
management system for you guys to be able
to implement these security type-- or
these security requirements as well.
So the whole idea here is that we want
configurations to be dead-simple for any users.
We really don't want them to think about
it other than they set their passcode.
And we want these security requirements
to be fully manageable by enterprises.
And that's really the whole configuration story there.
So I'm going to turn it over to Mitch to talk a
little bit about adoption of these API's in your apps
>> Mitch Adler: So I'm going to talk a bit about
how you adopt Data Protection in your application.
To go back to what John was talking about a little
bit, we really want to protect your customer's data,
we want to protect all of our mutual customer's data,
we want you to assume the data needs protection.
You don't actually know what data users
are going to decide to put inside your app.
If you're making a note-taking app, they might
put their credit card number in your app.
It doesn't seem like a good idea
to me, but they might do it.
We need you to help put the data into the right class.
Since we don't automatically try and protect all your
data to preserve functionality of your application,
we need help from you to know how
you want that data protected,
so that we can do the best protection we can for the user.
We recommend you find the most protected
class, and we'll get it to how you decide
on what's the most protective class you can.
It's here.
We also want you to help put the user data back
into places that's protected because the file system
and the Keychain are protected by Data Protection.
RAM, you have your user's information and
it's not protected by Data Protection.
So somebody can attack the device and get
into your process, which is not an easy feat.
But if they can do it, they can steal data that's in RAM.
So we recommend that you push the data out of RAM, push
it into the protected containers when the device locks.
So one of the first things you're
going to have to do when you're going
to adopt is analyze your data to
figure out what you need to protect.
You pretty much need to answer these four
questions, and you can figure out what class
and what location and how you want to protect that data.
The questions are what data of the users do I
have, do I need it when it's locked, you know,
does it belong in the Keychain, should it move from
device to device, and we'll get in to each one of these.
So how do I answer what data of the users do I have.
Well, it's everything they create.
It's all the data users are entering, and it's the
credentials that they enter to connect to things,
and it's credentials you create on their behalf, if you
make a connection and then wanted to create credentials
to make a persisting connection,
or reestablishable connection,
those credentials are data of the
users because it represents them.
Do I need that data when the device is locked?
Well, for most app writers, the answer is no.
If the device locks, your app doesn't do much, it's
waiting for the user to come back and interact with it.
So you don't.
But some background-aware applications are going to
need things like credentials, and they're going to want
to put those credentials in such a way that they
get protected, but they're still accessible.
Which is why we have the compromise
of AccessibleAfterFirstUnlock,
which is a good place to put things like credentials
you want to use and be able to reuse as users move
around their networks but want to get some protection from
the classical kinds of compromises, which involve a reboot.
Then you have to ask does it belong on the Keychain.
This is a question we've talking about for a very long time.
Credentials belong on the Keychain, particularly,
things that you want to migrate around.
Things like passwords, keys, identities you've
establish for the user or imported for the user.
Large bulk data doesn't really
belong on the Keychain itself.
Should it move from device to device?
Well, the simple answer is yes.
The user wants their stuff to move from device to device.
But the more complex answer is, well, unless you have
some compelling reason then it doesn't, and you'll--
you in this room will probably aware of
why you would want that to be the case.
We have an example on our system when you import VPN
configuration profile, and you set up a VPN identity,
that's the identity of the device, not of the user.
So those identities stay on the device.
They are not permitted to migrate from device to device.
But we have to make our system aware of the fact
that those might go away if I restore a backup.
I'll get half the data back, but I won't get the migrated
VPN identity, and I'll have to deal with that state.
So if you don't have a compelling reason to make
it non-migratable, make your data migratable.
So we'll go through a few examples to help clarify this.
The first example I have is a theoretical game.
I have a game that has some online
play, it has some credentials it stores.
It has some saved games it stores.
That's pretty much all the data we have from the user.
So for each one of these, I've gone through the questions.
Do I need access to the credentials
when the device is locked?
Well, no, my game has stopped and the device is locked.
I don't need to connect to my server.
It's-- we're done at that point.
Do I need it to migrate?
Well, it's credentials and the user would
like to be able to reconnect to our server
if they migrate to a new piece of hardware.
So, yeah, I'd like it to migrate.
Does it belong in the Keychain?
It's a credential.
It belongs on the Keychain.
So I'm going to put it on the Keychain and I'm going
to give it the attribute AccessibleWhenUnlocked,
the best protection I can.
I also have saved games which have similar attributes.
Yes I-- actually, no, I do not need access to them
when they're locked, yes, I want them to migrate,
but, no, they don't belong on the Keychain.
So the protection class I give them is
ProtectionComplete, and I use their location
on the file system to control their migration.
I put them in my documents folder in my app, and those
automatically get me moved into my backup and moved back
to my app, and they're accessible when
I won't migrate from device to device.
Second example is an online service.
So suppose I have an online service
that has decided to participate
in a new background task completion multitasking type, and
it has some credentials, it has some data that is trying
to push up to the server in the background, or it's trying
to not burden the user with failing to push my photo
up to the server, and it has some
cash data it wants to display
because it's got some stuff it's pulled
down from the server for fast access.
And all of these are user data.
So start with the service credentials.
I have some service credentials that I do need
when it's locked because I'm participating
in background task completion, and I might
change networks and need to reconnect
to actually complete the operation I'm doing with my server.
So next question is do I want to migrate this data?
Well, it's credentials, they belong to a user, I'm-- I
pretty much want it to migrate so my service will work
on the new device it get to right out the box.
And does it belong in the Keychain?
Well, yes, it's a credential.
It belongs in the Keychain.
So the protection I give it is AccessibleAfterFirstUnlocked.
This is the second category of protection.
It's not quite as good, as AlwaysIsProtectedWhenUnlocked,
but it does give us some protection
against the task that require a reboot.
So we choose the second best protection
because we want the user experience to be good.
The second class of data we have
is a data that's being uploaded.
So I have some data the users put in the background.
Do I want this access to the data when it's locked?
Yes. Do I want this data to migrate?
No, this is an in-process operation.
This data's going to go up to the server.
I don't need this data to move.
Does it belong on the Keychain?
No it doesn't belong on the Keychain.
It's bulk data, it's a big file.
So I have to put it on the file
system, and I've put in ProtectionNone.
We have to admit we did not provide file
system API's to get to the second class.
We didn't think they were as valuable as they might be,
and if you find reasons why they are
interesting to you, we'd love to hear them.
This is a case where it might be interesting, but in
this case, we choose ProtectionNone and we put the file
in a place it doesn't migrate, which would be the
cache's directory in your application, for example.
Cash data, on the other hand, we don't need when the device
is locked, because it's for-- presenting data to the user.
And when the device is locked, we
don't present anything to the user.
We don't need this to migrate, it's caches.
We might choose to.
But in this case, we don't care to.
Does not belong on the Keychain.
It's large data.
So we put it in ProtectionComplete which
protects it when the device is locked,
and we put in it our caches directory so it doesn't migrate.
The final example is a relative
simple example if I make a diary.
It's a place somebody can record their
thoughts, whatever they want to put in there,
their credit numbers because they are crazy.
So I have this diary which is on the device, and we
don't need it when it's locked because it's for the user.
We do want it to migrate, and we don't want another Keychain
because its large unknown pictures,
whatever they use or want to enter.
But we do want to protect it.
So we put it in ProtectionComplete.
This allows it to be protected with Data
Protection, and we put it in our documents folder
for our app, probably the simplest example of all.
So once you've made your protection choices, and you've put
your data into an appropriate class, there is one more thing
that you want to do when you adopt,
particularly, if you are an app that's running
on the background or running while the systems is locked.
Your app does not really care with the systems is locked,
and just pretty much left this data on the file system
and tries to quit if the system locks,
you'd-- there's not a lot you have to do here.
But if you are a background app, or want to
operate while the system is heading towards lock,
there are some stuff you need to do.
There is a notification that comes through.
There is actually a symmetric one for this also,
that says protection data will become unavailable.
This is a symmetric one that says become
available, but it's less interesting.
It's just telling you, you get your data back, and
then you can choose to access your data at that point.
This one is relatively important
because it does give you a moment
in which you can help enforce the security of the users' data.
In response to this notification, we ask that you
purge the data in memory that is not necessarily--
that is not necessary when the device is locked.
Specifically, we want you to take the data that
needs protection, put it back into the containers
that it's supposed to be protected
in, and close those containers.
So you push it back in the file system, you push it back
on the Keychain, you get it out of your local address base,
so that if somebody is clever enough to grovel
your memory, they won't get that data either.
In order to make our system actually have a predictable
behavior about locking, we have to give an upper bound
to how long an application can hold us off
from causing the system to actually lock.
So you actually have-- only have 10
seconds to complete this notification.
If you don't complete this operation in 10
seconds, we're going to lock the device behind you.
The reason why that is interesting
is once the device is locked,
you don't get access to the data
that's in the highest protection class.
You will actually get errors trying to reach in the files
to get EPERM errors saying, no, can't read that data.
We want you to be resilient to those kinds of failures,
not necessarily your app has to keep chugging along
and doing great, but don't crash, don't do spectacularly
bad things for the user, considering that that might happen.
To move on to some interfaces in the file system.
So how do I create and set this attributes.
I need to help the system know.
There are two API's we've added to help
you communicate to the file system,
what protection class, you want your data in.
The first is in NSData writeToFile,
there are new options added.
The file that is created will get the ProtectionComplete
or ProtectionNone, depending on the option you include.
The second is NSFileManager, has an API to set an
attribute of the file, which is the protection key,
which will then set the class of the
file, the protection class of the file.
You can use this on any existing file on the file system.
It's sticky.
And then once you set the class for the file, it retains
that class in the file, you don't have to tell us again.
And most importantly, you can use any other file system
access you want to, and then it will operate normally,
except for the fact that if the device locks, and it's in
a locked class, we'll get errors when trying to access it.
So if you are creating a file to hand
off to another subsystem on your device,
you can set its class before you hand it off.
If you know you've requested a file you created by
some other system, you can find it, set its class.
The other thing we need to point out is that your
existing files that have been run long, your documents
and your documents folder are not going to have
any protection classes except ProtectionAlways.
So if you want to protect that data for the user, which
we hope you do, you need to actually find those documents
and set the protection class on
the files in those documents.
So choosing your protection on the file
system, this actually will be simple.
Use ProtectionComplete, you know, protect the user's data.
Right up until you find a good reason
that you can't protect their data.
You need to use it when you are in the
background, this is probably the most popular.
I really can't think of many other
reasons why you wouldn't want
to protect the user's data, although
you might come up with some.
The Keychain has new interfaces, now just
new attributes on its existing interfaces.
SecItemAdd and SecItemUpdate have always taken
a query with the dictionary of parameters in it.
There's a new attribute case like accessibility.
You can give it one of these values, and that
will set the accessibility of your Keychain item.
Just like the file system, the
Keychain needs update if you want
to change the accessibility class of a given Keychain item.
By default, when we move the Keychain back to the device
it came from because all backups that are currently
out in the world, can only move back to the same device,
all the Keychains out there will go back to the same device.
But when it returns to that device, we set all the data
to AccessibleAlways, which you should note is migratable.
So if you really, don't want it to be migratable, you
should hit it with the hammer and tell it not to migrate.
If you think it should be less protected because
you want to operate in the background now,
your app's updating and wants to upgrade in the background.
You may want to set its protection class
to be type to, AccessibleAfterFirstUnlock.
If you don't need the data at all, except when you are
running unlocked, set it to AccessibleWhenUnlocked.
So summarize that basic decision tree, the other direction.
When you have data and you are trying to consider on
the Keychain, how am I going to protect this data?
You should start with the most restrictive, but we
recommend migratable, which is AccessibleWhenUnlocked.
That's probably the right class for the vast
majority of the data that is on the Keychain.
But if you find reasons that you need to access a
credential when it's locked, the most obvious one I thought
of is I need to get back to that server
because I was just told the network changed
and I still have stuff to talk to that server about.
Use AccessibleAfterFirstUnlock, that still
maintains some protection for the user's data,
but let's you do the background operation.
And if you really create data for this device
only, and really, if you create device--
for this device only, be sure it's for this device only.
And then you can make the user experience with that
data appropriate, and make it for this device only.
But if you suddenly discover that that data was for the
user, when they go to a new device, they won't get it.
So we recommended you think seriously
if you want it to stay on this device.
But you will know.
I mean, if you create a data that's for the device and
not for the user, that will be relatively obvious too.
So a quick example of modifying the access a SecItemAdd,
those of you who are using the
Keychain already will recognize this.
You build the query, you called SecItemAdd
with that query as data to the Keychain.
All you have to do is add one more set of attributes you put
in the query dictionary, kSecAttrAccessible, in this case,
accessible and unlocked is the--
actually what we're requesting.
And then you can use that SecItemAdd.
You can also use the SecItemUpdate.
So some way in our adoption, it's
relatively straightforward.
We're asking you to protect your users' data, we're asking
you to choose the strongest protection class you can,
and we're asking you to update the existing data
protection on the file system and on Keychain.
We're also asking that you use the Keychain.
It supports migration now.
That was a big hindrance before.
If people would put on the Keychain, they're-- you'd
migrate to a new device, your passwords would all be lost.
It was really irritating for users.
That's gone now.
So we think we have all the reasons
or mood to now use the Keychain.
So what we talked about today, John started talking
about why we want to help protect the user's data.
These devices are all more mobile, they're much more
active, they actively do access in the background.
The data on these devices are more
personal, and there's a lot more of it.
So it has higher value, particularly to an appointed
attack, and it looks and says, hey, I want Mitch's data,
I'm going to steal his phone, and get his data off of it.
And we're willing to help deal with this,
we want to tie the data to a user's secret.
That way, the user owns the secret, not us and not
our system, not penetrating the owner's system.
The data protection model is to
protect the data with the passcode.
So all the user data is supposed to protected with a
passcode to strengthen against devices that get compromised.
So if somebody takes my device, they can break through
the front barriers that we think are pretty strong,
but are not perfect, if they get through that,
they still have to get through the
cryptographic protection with the user's passcode.
We also protect the user passcode by tying its derivation to
a key to the hardware, so that brute force on that passcode,
even if I have all the data inside the
device, if I've gotten into the device,
requires I do operations on the device to attack it.
I can't send it out to my botnet and get
a factor of a million on my attacks speed.
We want data protection to always be on.
It is always on when the user set his passcode.
You can't have it off.
You got a new passcode, data protection comes on.
And to reiterate again, there is no performance impact.
We're already encrypting and decrypting data as it goes
to and from the file system, and to and from the Keychain.
All we've done in this update is change
the architecture of what keys we use
when we push the data in and out of the storage systems.
And lastly, we talked about was how you guys adopt
and help us make all the user's data protected.
We're asking that all applications protect the user's data.
Since user information is all over the place, any
application where I can have a text deal and enter data,
I could put something that I want protected.
We're adopting it.
We're adopting it as quickly as we can.
We chose mail first since it was one of our most
complicated ones to prove out that the technology worked.
We're definitely going to be adding more apps.
We're asking you to put your data into appropriate classes,
to update your existing data into the appropriate classes,
and we really are trying to encourage
you to use the Keychain.
We think there are no excuses left to
not use the Keychain for credentials.
So if you are interested in any more
information about the presentation,
you can contact our Evangelist
or you can check out the forms.
There are few related sessions.
The first ones of the Multitasking on iPhone have already
occurred, but there is rerun of them tomorrow morning.
And, if you want to pay attention to
how you handle being a multitasking app,
because those moments will be interesting
for you to decide about data protection.
The Managing Mobile Devices session was last Tuesday.
You can catch the replay when they are posted.
It talks about how to configure
devices and manage them remotely.