>> Vicki Murley: Hi everyone I'm Vicki Murley the Safari
Technologies Evangelist at Apple is this is Session 501:
Delivering Audio and Video using Web Standards Part 1.
So how many of you out in the audience are
using a plug-in to display audio or video?
If you could just show of hands please.
Ok great and how many of you are using
HTML5 on iPad but a plug-in everywhere else?
How many people are in that boat?
Ok a couple.
And how many of you are using HTML5 everywhere you possibly
can, in every browser, on every platform that supports it?
Can I get a show of hands?
Ok small group that last one.
Ok well whichever group you happen to be in I can guarantee
you're going to learn something in this session today
that you can go back and implement immediately once
you leave this session or leave the conference.
So you've probably been hearing a lot about HTML5 these
days, in fact you have been hearing a lot about it
and there's one thing that kind of caused people to sit
up and take notice with regard to HTML5 and that's iPad.
So iPad is technically a mobile device but like
iPhone OS like iPhone it does not support plug-ins,
however it has this very large
screen, so users browsing the web
on iPad are really expecting a desktop
caliber, full fledged browsing experience.
If you have audio or video on your
website, they want to see it on iPad.
So since there are no plug-ins on iPad this really - this is
a device that caused a lot of website developers to sit up
and take notice and take a good hard
look at web standards for the first time.
So you've probably seen this site before.
apple.com/ipad/ready-for-ipad and if you've
ever surfed the web you've probably seen
at least one of the sites that are listed here.
So there's quite a few: CNN, Vinio, NPR, People.com,
Life, America's Finest News Source, theonion.com.
These are all websites that are moving to HTML5 to deliver
a great experience on iPad and in particular HTML5 audio
and video elements to deliver a great experience.
So I actually worked with quite a few of these
developers to get them started with HTML5 audio and video
and that's what I'm going to do with
you today, help you do the same thing.
So in this session I'm going to cover 3
main areas: the first is pretty simple,
just adding media to your web pages with HTML5.
After that I'm going to talk about how to optimize
that experience with standard web technologies
and finally I'm going to discuss how you can
use built-in functions to control your media.
As I mentioned I work with developers a lot so along
the way as we're going through those 3 main topics,
I'm going to address some of the most common questions
that I've heard from developers just like you.
So let's get started talking about
adding media to web pages with HTML5.
So in this section I'm going to tell you
how you can specify fall back content,
how you can write cross browser compatible
code and I'm also going to talk to you
about some platform specific considerations
if you're deploying media
with HTML5 on iPad or iPhone versus the desktop.
So let's get started with the basics.
So this is just one line of code and with this
boom you're done, you have video in your webpage.
It's pretty great.
I want to just take one moment to point out that everything
I'm going to talk about today is true for both the video tag
and the audio tag so there's really only 5 attributes
that are different, that are unique to the video tag,
poster image, height and width
and video height and video width,
those last two are the native height and width of the video.
Everything else is the same for the
two elements but most of my examples
and code snippets et cetera are
going to focus on the video tag.
So let's get back to our basic tag again.
If we want to display some fall back content in web
browsers that don't support the HTML5 video tag,
we simply nest that content in
between the opening and closing tags
so here we're falling back to a
plug-in to display our movie.
Here we're just showing a static image
and here we're showing some text.
You can really put anything you like in
between these opening and closing elements.
Also on our simple example here we have a
source attribute and you can really throw a lot
at this source attribute and it just works.
So for example, in Safari on the desktop the video and
audio elements will play any linear codec supported
by QuickTime and this includes user installed codecs.
In Safari on iOS you can play H.264 video
with a baseline profile, uncompressed WAV
and AIF audio, and MP3 AAC-LC and HE-AAC audio.
It's also worth noting there are
a couple of other types of media
that you can provide to that source
attribute that just work.
Those are QuickTime reference movies and also HTTP Streams.
So you can point that source attribute at your streaming
media, at that URL and it will just work in Safari.
Ok back to our simple example one more time.
So we have this opening video tag, closing video tag and our
fallback content in between which just is a line of text.
So it's worth noting and it trips people up a little
bit sometimes that this text is only displayed
if the browser does not implement, does not support
the HTML5 video tag at all so in cases where you point
to a media resource that can't be played, or
something like that because it's in a codec
that the browser doesn't understand,
that fallback text won't be shown.
It's only shown if the browser
doesn't implement the video tag.
So how can we deal with that?
Well one answer is to use the source tag and
you can put source tags in between your opening
and closing video elements, video tags and what happens is
the browser sees these and they iterate through this list
of source tags and they play the
first encoding that they can play.
A couple of tips when you're using the source
tag is number 1, to specify a type attribute.
So if you don't specify a type attribute, the browser
actually has to download a piece of the video to see
if it can play it before it can move onto the next
one so you can avoid unnecessary network requests
and optimize performance a little
bit if you always specify a type.
You should also include in that type attribute
you can include a string of codecs so basically
with this source tag you're asking the
browser a question: Can you play this video?
The more information you give the
browser, the better answer it can provide.
So if you provide additional information here like
codec information, the better answer you will get.
So here we have 2 different codecs, they're both H.264 video
but one is a baseline profile and
the other is a high profile.
Another tip for using the source tag - it's really great
for just multiple media resources in general so just
like you might use a CSS media query to serve different
CSS files to different devices iPhone, or iPad,
or the desktop you can use those same queries
here in the media attribute on a source tag.
So in this first example here I'm serving this smaller
file, maybe it's a smaller dimensions to a device
that is probably an iPhone and in the second source tag
here I have a different file, it's larger dimensions,
I want to serve that to anything bigger than an iPhone.
Ok so we've talked about using the source tag
to go through different encodings to see whether
or not the browser can play that given encoding but what
if you just want to have one encoding and you want to see
if the browser can play that encoding
and supports the HTML5 video tag?
Well here's what you do.
The first step is to detect whether or not the
current browser supports the HTML5 video element
so you can just check HTMLVideoElement in window here.
The next step is to detect whether or not the browser
can play your media using the canplay type function
so here we've checked to see if
the browser supports HTML5 video.
Now we've created a video element and on
that video element we're calling canplay type
and just like you saw the type attribute earlier on
the source tag we're going to specify the same type
of string here, a mime type and a string of codecs.
So this string that you're passing to
canPlayType it has a lot of information in it
but it doesn't have all the information
that the browser needs to in order
to determine whether or not it can play the video.
For example, we can't know the bit rate, so
canPlayType can't conclusively tell you whether
or not it can play the video but it can get pretty
close, it provides one of three answers: probably, maybe,
and no are the three return values from canPlayType.
Codecs they're crazy.
So if it's maybe or probably you're in pretty good shape
so I'm going to set some extra attributes on my video tag
or video element that I created earlier and then
I'm going to append that element to the body.
Ok so now we're moving onto some
platform-specific differences between Safari
on the desktop and Safari on iPad and iPhone.
So here's my basic video tag once again with just a little
bit of text for fall back content and if I loaded that file
in Safari on the desktop, Safari on iPad,
and Safari on iPhone here's what I would see.
So the first thing that you're going to notice is
that on the far right you're going
to see that controls are displayed.
So iPhone always displays controls.
The video is played in full screen mode all
the time and we always show our own controls
over the video, so controls are always shown on iPhone.
The second thing you're going to notice is that these
videos are different sizes so I haven't specified a height
and width on my video tag and so on iPad and iPhone
we get a default height and width of 150x300 pixels
and this is per the HTML5 spec. What's happening here
behind the scenes is the default behavior on the desktop is
to auto buffer download and auto buffer the video.
So even though we haven't specified a height and width,
the browser knows the height and width of the video,
just like when you specify a image in a webpage
and you don't specify a height and width.
The browser can infer that information
from the media, in that case the image.
So on iPad and iPhone there's no automatic buffering.
We don't want our users to be on a cellular
network and incur involuntary data charges
so we don't auto buffer this media on iPad and iPhone so in
that case we can't infer the dimensions
and we have to give a default dimension.
So luckily it's very easy to make one simple change
to this video tag to make all of these look the same.
I'm just going to specify a height of 240, a width of
320 and I'm also going to add the controls attribute
which is a boolean attribute so even the existence of it
turns it on so I could even have controls equals false here
but it would still be there, it's boolean attribute
so the controls would still be on in that case.
Here I've just set it with no value whatsoever and doing
that will cause my video to look like this on all platforms.
All the same size that we would expect it to be and controls
that match the platform, so some controls on the desktop
and then same controls on iPad and iPhone.
Ok so that's one sort of platform-specific detail.
Let me tell you about a few more.
Safari on Mac OS X in windows is optimized for
concurrent playback of multiple media resources
so you can play two videos at once, an audio and a video
file at once, two audio files at once, more than two,
whatever you want to do, you can play multiple
files at the same time on the desktop.
You also have programmatic volume control on the desktop
so you would set change the volume via the volume
and muted properties on the video or audio
element and that is available on the desktop.
And as I mentioned before automatic buffering
is enabled by default so things like autoplay,
the autoplay attribute on an audio or video tag which will
start your video automatically, or calling the play function
from an on-load handler or something like that, something
where the user has not explicitly triggered playback,
both of those things will work on the desktop.
On iOS, iOS is optimized for playback from a single
media resource, so only one media resource at a time.
Volume is under user control.
You notice that in this screen shot I don't have the little
volume control that I had on my previous screen shot,
these are my own controls that I
drew myself and on iOS I removed them
because the volume cannot be changed programmatically.
This is true for native iOS applications as well.
You don't want one of the apps that you installed
or a script from a webpage muting your volume
and missing a phone call so volume is under user
control on iOS and finally, as I mentioned earlier,
there's no automatic buffering on iOS and this
means that things like autoplay do not work.
Again we don't want our users to incur data
charges involuntarily and if you call play
from your on-load handler not a result of a explicit user
action to click a play button, that will not work on iOS.
Ok so that covers the first section:
Adding Media to Your Web Pages with HTML5,
now let's move onto Optimizing the Media
Experience with Standard Web Technologies.
Ok so I mentioned a couple of times that autoplay or calling
the play function in line is only supported on the desktop
and I want to give you a real world example of how
that affects the different events that are emitted
by the HTML5 audio and video tags so
I'm going to switch to the demo machine.
Ok can barely see you guys now but oh well.
So I'm going to load this simple file and this is basically
a simple video tag, I have the controls attribute set
and then I have a bunch of event listeners added that
log a message to the page whenever an event is emitted.
So here you can see load start and duration change
have fired, I'm going to show some notes here
and explain a couple of the non-obvious ones.
Load in metadata is very important.
At this point you know the height and width of the video.
Loaded data tells us that the browser can render
the media data at the current playback position.
In this case its zero time.
Progress tells us it's fetching the
media, this is a pretty small file,
it's only 42 seconds so we only
have one progress event here.
Canplay tells us we can play the media but we might
have to buffer to play it all the way to the end
and canplaythrough tells us we can play it all
the way through and won't have to buffer anymore.
So I'm just going to start playing this media and you can
see a couple of things have happened we got this play event
which tells us we just returned from the play
function, playing tells us playback has started
and we received several time update events here as well.
So time update is emitted anywhere
from 3-5 times per second here.
So I'm just going to collapse those and then I'm
going to load the same file on iOS on iPhone.
So you can see right away that the first frame of
this video is black and also we get two events here:
We get a load start event and a suspend event so the
load start tells us that media has started downloading
and the suspend event tells us that loading has
stopped but not all of the media has downloaded.
So now I'm going to play this video,
its Johnny talking about iPad
and now full screen mode which is the default on iPhone.
So I'm just going to click done and the
interesting thing that you should note here is
that JavaScript is still running even when my video is
playing in full screen mode so I'm still getting all
of the events that you would expect to get, even when
you know the video is taking over the whole screen.
So here we had our load start and suspend, we click the
Play button here, we were waiting a little bit for some
of the media, we got a duration change event, a lot
of these are the same as the desktop, loaded metadata
and loaded data, canplay so at this point
we immediately start playing the media
because we clicked the Play button way back here.
We get a progress event telling us that the media is
being fetched, canplay through, load and then pause
and of course all of these time update events as well.
So that's it in a nutshell how events work with
the video tag in Safari on the desktop and on iOS.
So this is actually really important because understanding
when these events are emitted are really critical
if you want to kind of enhance the user experience,
create your own controls, add a progress indicator,
anything like that you need to have a good
understanding of when these events are firing.
So the sample that I just showed should be associated with
this session as sample code and I would really encourage you
to experiment with that file, try out
different devices, different media sources,
try a streaming source, try a very large resource.
Here we just got one progress event but if you
had a very large resource you would get many
and also software versions.
The HTML5 spec for video is changing a little bit.
One concrete example is that the load event has been removed
so that is something that may change in the future in Safari
so try different software versions as well.
Ok so we saw just now the default
behavior on both platforms.
Auto buffered on the desktop, not auto buffered on iOS
but what if I wanted to disable automatic buffering
on the desktop, so maybe I have a video blog and I have
like 10 videos on the front page and I don't want them all
to start downloading at once because that would use up
a lot of bandwidth and it wouldn't be great performance
so I want to just disable automatic buffering.
Well there is a new attribute that is available in Safari
5 and it's this pre-load attribute and you can just set it
to none and auto buffering is disabled, which is great.
So that's new in Safari 5 but what
about users who may still have Safari 4?
You might want to disable auto
buffering for those users as well.
Well thanks to the power of JavaScript that's easy to do
as well so here we have our video element and you'll notice
that the source attribute is blank,
it's just an empty string so basically
when the browser encounters a video tag it'll look at that
source attribute and if there's anything there it's going
to try to start pulling that media immediately.
If there's nothing there it has nothing to pull so
we also set a little event handler here for a click
and when we click on this video element
we call this set source function.
We get our video element and we just set the source
attribute to the URL of our media, in this case iPad.m4v.
Then we programmatically play and everything is great,
no automatic buffering in older versions of Safari.
A couple of other, I want to point out a
couple of other useful things about events,
basically when you should do what as far as events go.
So loaded metadata is a really important one so
here we are setting height and width on the fly.
Earlier in this discussion I mentioned how you'll get
a default height and width if you don't specify one.
Sometimes it's not always possible to hard
code that height and width into your video tag.
You might be serving the video on the
fly and not know the height and width.
So you can set these attributes on the fly and resize
your video pretty easily so here we're listening
for a loaded metadata event and when we get it we're
going to set height and width, very straight forward,
we're just getting our video element and we're
looking at the native video height and video width
and we're setting the height and
width attributes accordingly.
So this will resize your height and width on the fly.
Loaded metadata is also really important
if you want to trigger full screen mode.
So this is now supported in Safari 5, its new.
Saw it at the State of the Union
yesterday, it was mentioned.
This is really cool so we have again our simple
video tag listening for loaded metadata event
in this case we're calling a function
called checkFullscreenSupport.
We also have a button on this page, this button is
actually what's triggering full screen mode and it's doing
that by getting our video element
and calling webkitEnterFullscreen.
So this is our button that's triggering
full screen mode in our user controls.
So back to our check full screen support function
here which is called once the metadata is loaded,
at this point you need to check and see if the
video element, or it could even be an audio element,
if that supports full screen mode so if it
doesn't support full screen mode I'm going
to want to hide that button that triggers it.
So if you're drawing your own custom controls this
is a really great technique you you know don't want
to present controls to the users that
don't work so always check to see
if full screen mode is supported
for those types of controls.
Ok other useful events that are emitted by HTML5 media
elements are canplay, canplaythrough and waiting.
These are great opportunities to show a
progress indicator to let your user know
that something's happening but they
just have to wait a little bit.
We're not going to show any code snippets for this one
because Beth Dakin is going to walk us through the code step
by step and show us exactly how to listen for these
events and optimize the user experience so Beth.
[ applause ]
>> Beth Dakin: Thanks Vicki.
So I put together a little webpage
today that just shows a video,
I'd like to share it with you and
it's really pretty straight forward.
So let's just dive straight into the code.
So here's my HTML file I just have
14 lines of HTML, very simple stuff,
this should look pretty familiar at this point.
Here's my video element I just have
an ID on it, a width and a height.
I specify the controls attribute so that I
get the default controls on each platform.
I have the source pointing to my media resource which is
a beautiful short film called Dartmoore by James Watson -
highly recommend it - and finally I've specified the poster
attribute to have pointing to a ping that I have that I want
to display as a poster image and I have
a little bit of fall back content too
and then I just have a link down
here to James Watson's webpage.
I just have a tiny bit of CSS, which isn't especially
relevant to this so we won't really focus on it
so let's take a look at what this looks like in iPad.
[ pause in speaking ]
So here you go I have my poster image displayed
here, I get the default controls and I can
[ music ]
Let's take a look at this in Safari 5.
So you may have noticed a little something different here.
We're no longer showing a poster image so let
me explain what's going on there a little bit,
the HTML5 specification defines a poster image as
something that shows when no data is available,
so as Vicki explained earlier the default behavior
on Safari on the desktop is to auto buffer the video.
So once enough of the video has auto buffered
the poster image won't display anymore
and so what we're seeing instead is the first frame of the
video which happens to be black so now I can play my video
[ music ]
There you go.
So with just a few lines of HTML I've got a really good
out of the box experience here for the HTML5 video element
but the fact that this is so good out of the box is really
only half of what's awesome about HTML5 video element.
Really the other half is that it's totally customizable,
it's within your power and control as a designer
to make this look however you want so there
are a few things that I want to change here.
First of all I don't think I want a poster image, what I
really want is an image overlay that's going to display
over the video until the user starts playing it and
instead of just disappearing and going to the first frame
of the video like a poster image, I want it to fade out
nicely which is an effect we can easily achieve with CSS
and I also want a custom play button that will be
the same on all platforms so that's kind of a lot
so let me show you what I want to achieve
and then I'll show you the code to do it.
Ok so this is what I want here we are on Safari 5.
We still have that image because it's not a
poster image, it's instead an image overlay
and it's still there and I have my custom button.
So let's take a look at the code.
[ pause in speaking ]
Ok here's my HTML it has not changed
much, it's only a few lines longer.
We have 20 lines of HTML now instead of 14.
My video element should look pretty much the same.
I've removed the poster image attribute.
Here I've added a DIV element that I'm calling my status
DIV this is going to be that click to play button.
I also have an image element, this is the image
overlay, it's pointing to the same ping resource
that I was formally using as a poster image but
now it's my image overlay and I've also added
to my body tag here I've added an on load handler I'll call
a function init and I've also added a little job script file
so let's take a look at that init function.
Here it is in my JavaScript file.
Basically the point of this function is to just add a few
event listeners for various events that I want to handle
when that click to play button is clicked so I have
a little bit of local variable stuff here at the top,
just to take care of most down, most up, touch start,
touch end etc, cover all my bases with desktop and iOS
and then the first one here when I get any
of those up events I want to call load video
so that's a function I've defined right here.
Let's take a look at that.
Load video will just get that video, add an
event listener to the video itself so that
if we get the canplay event then we'll
call another function play video.
We also load the video here and here we're setting
the controls attribute on the fly instead of doing it
in the HTML and this is just so our
click to play button is clickable,
we don't want the default controls handling those clicks
so we're just going to set this when the video is loading.
So the play video function is the one
we'll call when we get that canplay event
and here what we're doing is just changing class names
for the image overlay and the click to play button,
the status DIV and then I'm telling the video to play
programmatically but this is a really common technique
that any of you familiar with web development, which
is probably a lot of you, are probably familiar with
but basically we're just switching out class
names here, what we really want to achieve
in this function is just changing around some CSS and
rather than writing out a bunch of lines of JavaScript
to individually manipulate the CSS attributes on
each of these elements, I'm just changing class names
so changing these [inaudible] class names hidden which I
have defined in my style sheet will just cause their opacity
to be 0, their Z index -1, they'll be out of the way and
basically all the rest of the JavaScript in this function,
excuse me this file is just devoted to toggling
the appearance of that click to play button
so that it disappears appropriately and one other thing I
want to point out here is I've also defined some transitions
in my CSS just here so that my image
overlay and my click to play button
at status DIV will fade out nicely with the transition.
It's really this simple, if you
don't know about transitions,
or you want to know more there are two sessions
later today: CSS Effects Part 1 and Part 2
that I strongly encourage you to
attend to learn more about that.
So let's take a look at this in action
[ Background music ]
So there we go I have a poster image
and it faded out nicely [inaudible].
And we have the same experience on iPad
[ music ]
So we have a pretty fast network right now and so this
video is loading pretty quickly but you can imagine
that if we were on some kind of cellular
network, or having some kind of network problems,
this might take awhile to load and it might be a little
bit confusing to users who just clicked that button
and see nothing happening yet cause
the video is not ready to play.
So I think I want to enhance this some
more by adding some progress indication.
Also if the resource wasn't available it seems
like my user would get a pretty bad experience too.
So if I just change the source attribute on my video to
something that doesn't exist and then I reload this page
and try to play it, nothing's happening here.
So this is not a great experience so I think
we should add some error handling as well.
[ pause in speaking ]
So let's take a look at that.
So I'm going to add some progress indication and error
handling so I don't' need to change my HTML to do that.
Over here in the JavaScript I don't need to
change either of these functions up here in it,
our toggle button appearance so I've just collapsed them.
Here I'm taking I'm doing some more of that class
name manipulation I mentioned earlier and I'm going
to change the class name of that status DIV
which was our click to play button to progress.
So if we look over at our CSS file to see what progress
is that's going to change the content of that progress DIV
to an animated gif so if we look at my resources that's
just this simple animated gif with a few frames that I have
of like a spinning progress indicator
back here in the script.
I also wanted to add error handling so I'm adding another
event listener here for the error event and if we get
that event then we will call our new report error
function which also just does class name manipulation
on that status DIV and we'll change the class name to error
where instead of that animated gif we'll have some text.
So let's take a look at this.
[Background music] So there we have the nice progress
indication; we got to see the video is loading,
it took awhile, but it would make
a lot more sense to our users.
And finally if the resource is actually not available
then we also get some nice indication to that
and again this all works the same on an iPad.
[music] So that's all for now I think I'll
hand it back to Vicki thanks everybody.
[ applause ]
>> Vicki: Al right thanks Beth.
That was pretty cool.
So there are a lot of pretty cool things about that demo.
I just wanted to point a couple of them out.
First, we basically we're noticing that HTML5
video is just like any other web page element.
You can layer it with other elements; here we have
that button overlaying an image
which was overlaid over the video.
You can style it with CSS, not sure if you noticed
but there was a little box shadow around the video,
that was just CSS applied directly to the video
element and also it can be manipulated with JavaScript.
Now the power of JavaScript in the DOM here
allowed us to add a lot of enhancements
to that basic video tag pretty quickly
so that was pretty cool thank you Beth.
Ok so that covers Part 2 Optimizing Your Media Experience
with Standard Web Technologies and now we're going to move
onto the final section here: Using
Built in Functions to Control Media.
So a lot of websites out there are doing a really great
job just using basic, the built in standard controls
so here's America's finest news
source, The Onion displaying video
with just the controls attribute, no custom controls at all.
But it's actually pretty simple to add your
own custom controls and we're going to look
at a very common control here, a play/pause button.
So it's pretty simple to do.
We basically have our video tag
at the bottom, is that built in?
Yes it is.
So we have our video tag at the bottom.
We have a button here which says play/pause
on it and when it's clicked we're going
to call this play/pause function here and this
is basically getting our video and checking
to see if it's paused via the pause property.
If it is paused, we're going to play it and
otherwise we're going to programmatically pause it.
So pretty straight forward, not very many lines of
code and to show us exactly how that works I want
to bring Beth back to the stage to add a Play/Pause button
[ applause ]
>> Beth: Thanks Vicki.
Let's see ok so we're going to
add a play/pause button to this.
So here's my HTML again and it hasn't changed
much, I've added one more element here,
another DIV and this one has the ID play/pause button.
If we look in our script file here I've rewritten this init
function a little bit because now I have a lot of buttons
so I've added this for loop so that all
of my buttons do these first two things,
which is to toggle the button appearance so that I
don't have to rewrite adding those event listeners
for every single button manually
and then for the special buttons
that need some extra event listeners
I've added this switch statement.
So this status case is an event listener that we
added before, we don't need to talk about that
but what's new is here we've also added a case for the
play/pause button so we'll add an additional event listener
for that button that whenever we get the up event we'll
call toggle, play, pause and so that I've defined down here.
I'm not going to get into this too much because it's
basically identical to what Vicki showed you on her slide,
it's pretty straight forward here we're just
programmatically calling play or pause as appropriate
and I'm also switching out some class names again to
get the appearance that I want further in the play case
or the pause case and the only other thing I want to point
out here is that I have also gotten rid of my line of code
that used to set that controls attribute programmatically,
because now we're drawing custom controls
so we don't want default controls.
So I'm just commenting out that line of code.
Oh and then the other thing is that I'm just
telling the play/pause button here to show
because initially it's not showing until we start playing
the video so I want to tell it to show here and it will fade
in nicely because I've added a
transition to my CSS file for that.
So let's take a look at this.
[ pause in speaking ]
[background music] So there you go you can see my custom
pause button in the corner there, no default controls.
I can click Pause and it toggles appropriately.
[background music] I can click Play again and you'll
see it has it's semi-opaque so it has this nice effect,
you can see the video playing behind it, it's
just another element layered on top of the video
and we can see the same thing whoops in iPad.
[ pause in speaking ]
[background music] There we go
[ applause and music ]
Thanks. Back to you Vicki.
>> Vicki: Beth oh you know what though like it
would have been really cool if you had added
like a full screen button too since that's new in
Safari 5, like that Play/Pause button was pretty cool
but it would have been really cool if
you added a full screen button too.
>> Beth: Actually Vicki I do have a version
of the demo with a full screen button.
Why don't I show everybody?
[ pause in speaking ]
Ok so to add a full screen button again
we just need to add a few more lines.
Here in my HTML I've added another DIV,
this one has the ID full screen button.
If we looked over in the JavaScript
here we add another special case
for our full screen button, a special case event listener.
When we get that up event on the full screen button we will
enter full screen but you may recall you may have noticed
in my HTML the default the initial behavior of that
DIV that's the full screen button is to be hidden
so what we really want to control here is when
we show that full screen button and we want
to make sure we only show it when
we have full screen capabilities.
So we add the event listener here cause we want the
capability to always be there but we're only going
to show it down here in our play video function
so you may recall that play video is only called
when we get the canplay event so by the
time we get the canplay event we will know
if we have full screen video capabilities so
if we have it then we will show the button.
So let's take a look at that.
[background music] Click to play, I get my custom controls.
I have my new full screen button in the corner.
I can press it, we go full screen, then
I can collapse by clicking this button
or pressing escape and that's it, full screen button.
[ applause ]
>> Vicki: Thanks Beth that was pretty cool.
You know that was pretty cool how it like scaled
in and everything but this video it's kind
of big it would have been cool if our video was a little
smaller so that people could really see the scaling effect.
I mean no offense; it would have been
cool if we had something like that.
>> Beth: I do actually.
I can show everybody.
How about I do that?
[background music] So here's a version of my movie that's
kind of small but I can click it and go full screen.
Why don't we watch that slow motion?
There you can really see how nice that transition
is and that's just out of the box experience there.
You can see it's scaling up slowly, you can also
see the background fading out, it's pretty sweet.
[ applause ]
Ok I think I'll go back to your slides now if that's ok.
>> Vicki: All right sounds good.
All right thanks Beth.
So pretty quickly added our own custom play/pause button
that matched the look and feel of our video, pretty cool.
So just to recap what I've gone over today: First I
talked about adding media to your web pages with HTML5;
really simple to just add one line
of code and simple fallback as well.
After that we talked about optimizing the media delivery
experience with standard web technologies, just using CSS,
JavaScript the DOM to make your media look great and finally
we just really quickly cause it was really simple went
over how to use built-in functions
to create custom media controls,
in this case we just did a simple play/pause button.
So just a couple of thoughts to take
with you today when you leave this room:
I want you to remember that it's really easy
to add media to your web pages with HTML5.
Lots of websites are just doing it with one line
of code, using the default controls, super easy.
You can make it as basic or as sophisticated as you like.
You saw when Beth was you know building up our demo code
that she started with just one video tag and then added
to it as she went and made it pretty
sophisticated, pretty quickly and finally
if you're a web programmer you're already an expert at using
HTML5 audio and video, it's just another web page element
that you can style with CSS, manipulate with
JavaScript and get started with something pretty cool.
So for more information if you have
any questions you can contact me,
the Safari Technologies Evangelist at Vicki@apple.com.
There's some great documentation on the Safari Dev
center which his at developer.apple.com/safari.
Specifically, I would want to point out
the Safari HTML5 Audio and Video Guide.
It's a great document that tells you
everything you're going to need to know
about HTML5 media in Safari on all platforms.
The HTML5 Spec is always a great resource to see what
the latest and greatest is around HTML5 and finally,
announced yesterday we have Apple Developer Forums for
web developers just join the Safari Developer Program
and access is totally free which is pretty cool.
There are a lot of great sessions coming up this week
related to HTML5 media and web technologies in general.
A couple of specific ones that I wanted to point out to you:
In this room following this session we have
Delivering Audio and Video Using Web Standards Part 2.
We also have - I think its right after
that one, Advances in HTTP Streaming,
so if you want to set up streaming
media, don't miss that session.
This afternoon also in this room
we have CSS Effects Part 1 and 2.
These sessions are amazing.
You don't want to miss them.
They're going to show you how to add some really cool CSS
effects to your web pages, which also could apply to video
and finally on Wednesday there's
another great session on adding touch
and gesture detection to your web pages on iPhone OS.
So here we just had a really simple example where we used
touch down, I'm sorry, touch start and touch end instead
of mouse down and mouse up to just get really
direct manipulation of those buttons in our example.
This session is going to go way beyond that
to tell you everything that you need to know
and implement some pretty cool
stuff around down touch events.