>> Simon Fraser: Hi, my name is Simon Fraser and
I'm an engineer on the Safari and WebKit team.
And you probably saw the first in this two-part
series on CSS effects by Jing just now.
This is part two.
And in this session we're going to focus on some slightly
more complex systems effects using a photo gallery
as an example.
But we'll look at keyframe animations
and 3D effects in some amount of detail.
Now you've probably heard the term
HTML5 a lot in the news recently.
And as we mentioned, HTML5 formally is the name of
a specification, which is the next version of HTML5.
But informally, it's being used to cover a
sort of fairly broad range of web technologies.
And today we're going to learn how to
use one of those web technologies, CSS3,
to create some really rich, immersive web experiences.
And you'll learn how to get really good
performance and really nice animation,
both on iPhone, iPad, and on the desktop.
And then we'll be using a little bit of
JavaScript to sort of glue things together
and to create some of the really cool effects.
So we first released support for dynamic
CSS effects in Safari 3.1 and in iPhone 2.0.
And it's been really interesting to
see what people have used them for.
Of course on www.apple.com we've been
putting these effects to great effect,
creating lot of really neat interactive
content that lets people look
at the new products and see all the details about them.
And there are also people outside of
Apple who have been using these effects.
This is the page from www.panic.com
that describes the Transmit application.
And this makes really good use of transitions, transforms,
and animations to let users explore
the features of this application.
So from inside a web page, the user
can really get a feel for what it's
like to use the actual application
once they've downloaded it.
And then in the State of the Union
yesterday, you saw the HTML5 demos.
These, again, make great use of CSS
effects so I encourage you to go
and explore those and to download the code for those.
So all of this stuff, you know,
obviously is just web development.
If you already know a little bit
of CSS -- cascading style sheets --
it's a very small amount of additional knowledge
to use CSS effects and really spice up your pages.
In this session, pretty much everything I'm
going to talk to you about is CSS properties.
There's a little bit of use of the
document object model -- that's the DOM API.
And that's the API you use from JavaScript to modify
the page, listen for events, and things like that.
And of course JavaScript is the programming
language that we use to drive all this stuff.
And all of this works in Safari on iOS or on iPad, iPhone,
and iPod touch, and of course Safari on Mac and Windows.
And then if you're embedding WebKit in
your native apps, in UIWebView, in iOS,
and WebView on the desktop, all this stuff works as well.
And also, there's another client now -- iAds.
So if you're creating iAds, you'll probably
make really strong use of CSS effects.
So let me take a minute to talk about open standards,
and you've probably heard this
before, but I want to reinforce it.
The way Apple advances web technology
is to participate in open standards
and specifically we work with the standards groups.
For example, we've worked very closely with the
WHATWG Group and the HTML working group of the W3C
on the HTML5 specification, particularly
in terms of the audio and video elements.
I'm actually a member of the CSS working group and all the
properties that I'm going to talk about today are included
in specifications that we've submitted to the working
group for consideration, for inclusion in CSS3.
Now because these are still specifications in draft
form, we do have the WebKit prefix on the properties
and Jean mentioned in the previous
talk why we have this prefix.
So let me show you -- or tell you --
what you'll learn in today's session.
We're going to focus on two demos and use those to explain
to you what CSS effects you can
use and why you want to use them.
The first one is what we call a lightbox.
It's a simple image viewer.
You're probably really familiar with this -- you go to a
page with images or a gallery, you click on those images,
and then get this sort of full screen overlay or
full window overlay and you focus just on the image.
And in creating this lightbox, we'll see
how simple it is to use CSS transitions.
And we'll show you how to get consistent
behavior between iPhone, iPad, and desktop.
Now the second example is a photo gallery,
and this has some more dynamic content.
We're loading images dynamically,
there's a bit more JavaScript.
But we'll use this as a vehicle to show you the really
cool effects you can do with transitions, animations,
and transforms -- some really nice cinematic stuff.
And throughout the session I'll
give you some tips and tricks.
So to show you these two demos that we
built, I'd like to invite my colleague,
Enrica Casucci on stage to give you a demo.
[ Applause ]
>> Enrica Casucci: Hi, everyone.
I'm going to show you today a simple example of a lightbox.
As Simon said, a lightbox is a technique normally used to
display large images on top of a page using an overlay.
It's something that looks more or less like this.
Normally, the larger image is presented with a variety
of transitions, animations for positioning and sizing.
And there's a number of existing frameworks that you can
use in order to easily add this functionality to your pages.
The one we have used for this example is called FancyBox.
But let's take a look a little bit
closely at the transition here.
As I tap on the image, as you can see the transition
to the large image is not extremely smooth.
And let me do this one more time.
Notice that when the overlay comes up, there
is no opacity animation on the background.
And also, normally these frameworks provide some sort of
loading indicator while the large image is being loaded.
And let me show you this one slowly.
As you can see, the progress indicator looks fairly static.
What happens here is that even though -- I mean,
this is a great framework, don't get me wrong --
but the problem that we are encountering here is
that JavaScript is used to drive the animation.
What this means is that we normally have JavaScript
timers firing for each frame of the animation.
Using CSS transitions and animation allow us to basically
let the rendering engine in the browser do the heavy lifting
for us, taking advantage of the existing hardware
and potentially leveraging hardware
acceleration when it's available.
So let me show you now another example of another page
we've created using only CSS transitions and animations.
Again, the look is very similar but as I tap over
the image, look how smooth the transition is.
We've used a scaling transition here.
Let me do this one more time so
that you can fully appreciate.
And also check out the transition on the opacity of the
overlay, which adds a very nice touch and a polished look.
And if I show you this first one that I've created with
a slow motion, look how smooth the progress animation is.
And this is because we are truly leveraging
the power of the hardware acceleration.
During the second part of the session, Simon is going to
talk about photo galleries and you will learn how to use 2D
and 3D transforms and animations
to create some awesome effects.
Since you're all developers, I'm pretty sure that at this
point you all want to jump to the code and take a look.
But I want to tease you a little bit longer.
Here is an example of a photo gallery that we
have created to showcase some of the effects
that you can achieve with CSS transforms and animation.
Using a transform on the opacity, you
can create a crossfade effect like this.
Transform with translations allow you to create
push effects like this or a push down like this one.
With rotation, you can achieve spin effects
but it's when you start using 3D transforms
that you can truly add visual depth to your photo gallery.
And with the same amount of effort, you can create,
like, a revolving door effect like this one, or a cube.
A few lines of JavaScript will allow
you to do something like this --
this amazing tile drop effect, unfolding effects, sorry.
Isn't that awesome?
[ Applause ]
At this point, I'm going to hand it back to Simon,
who will show you how to create these
amazing things with just a few lines of CSS.
>> Simon Fraser: Thanks, Enrica.
That looked really good.
So let's start off by what we call
building a better lightbox.
And as Enrica mentioned, there's lots of
lightbox implementations out there already.
We're not trying to replicate the features of all those.
We're not trying to reinvent the lightbox
but we wanted to focus on a few things here.
The first thing is: how you can make use of CSS
transitions to get really nice, smooth, transition effects.
And you saw a bunch of them in the lightbox example.
The second one is: how we can create
a loading indicator just with CSS.
And then finally: how to get consistent behavior and
consistent performance on desktop, iPad and iPhone.
So all of this we can do in just 4 simple steps.
The first step is something that any lightbox does --
when the user clicks on one of the smaller images
on the page, we start loading the large image.
And this is just some simple JavaScript you're
probably familiar with, creating new image element,
registering an onload handler so we get notified when
the image loads, and then we set the source attribute
to start loading the high-resolution image.
Now the key here is we want to do this as soon as possible.
We're going to have this overlay
that fades in over a period of time.
So the sooner we kick off this load, the
sooner the user gets to see the final image.
Okay, the second step -- that's to start fading in
the overlay, which is this sort of semi-opaque box
that covers the rest of the page so we focus on this image.
And here we start using a bit of CSS, we're matching the
element with the ID overlay, using the selector right there.
And it starts off with an opacity zero, so it's transparent.
And then when we apply the visible class
to that, it's going to fade to opacity 1.
And as you probably saw in CSS Effects Part 1, normally
when CSS properties change, they change instantaneously.
But this gives a very jarring, kind
of disruptive appearance to the user;
it's much better if we can smooth out that change.
And with one line of CSS, we can do this.
We apply the transition property and we say that
we want opacity to transition over a half second.
And that gives us this nice, smooth, even curve here.
And if we wanted to, we could use
a linear timing function --
that will give us a constant rate
of change in the opacity property.
So it's very easy to get animations with transitions.
And you've probably seen -- in fact,
you have seen the shorthand used a lot,
WebKit transition but these are the longhand properties.
The first one specifies which other
properties you want to transition.
The second one specifies how long
the transition is going to take.
And then transition timing function
allows you to control that easing function
and you can do custom timing functions
with the cubic Bezier.
There are a bunch of easing functions built in.
And then as you saw in the previous
session, transition delay,
which is really useful for these neat building effects.
So let's go back to the overlay.
Now, here we have to write a little bit of JavaScript
that's going to create the overlay for the first time
and it uses createElement, which is one these DOM APIs.
And it sets the IDs overlay so we can identify
it from JavaScript and style it in CSS.
And then we append the overlay to the body element.
Now you might think at this point that if you set
the visible class name, both styles will apply,
the opacity one will give a nice transition.
But in actual fact, that doesn't quite work as you expect.
So let me take a moment to explain why
this doesn't behave quite as you expect.
Now the reason is: browsers actually
do some style coalescing under the hood
and I'll explain that with this example here.
Imagine you have this JavaScript, it's
setting the background color to red
and then immediately it sets the background color to blue.
Now the question is: does the browser
ever actually render that red color?
And the answer is no.
The browser's essentially throwing
away redundant style changes.
It batches up the style changes and red is
getting overwritten with blue right away.
So the only thing it's going to
do here is render that blue color.
Normally this doesn't matter but transitions are temporal.
So there's this temporal component now that
means that this actually becomes important.
Imagine we changed the JavaScript to something like this.
So here we're setting the transition property and we're
saying that we want background color to transition.
And now, again, do you expect to see an
animation between red and blue in this case?
Well, the answer is no, we don't get one
here, either and for the same reason --
the browser's coalescing those style changes and so the
only thing the browser actually renders is the blue color.
And that transition rule is there.
And so if we change the color later on
to something else, we'll get a transition
but we won't actually ever see the
red-to-blue transition in this case.
Now, there are a number of solutions to this problem
and the one we recommend using is setTimeout.
And what this does is allow you to run
a little bit of code after a delay.
In this case, we used the delay
zero but it's enough of a delay
that the browser gets a chance
to render the initial red color.
And now when the color changes to blue a little
bit later on, the browser is actually going
to then run the transition between red and blue.
So you get a nice transition there.
So let's go back to our overlay.
In this case the scenario is a little different
but essentially we've just appended
this element to the document.
But we're applying the visible class
right away so the browser's never going
to have a chance to render the opacity zero.
And so it won't run that transition.
The solution is to use the setTimeout.
And now we change the class name to Visible inside
the setTimeout and we'll see a nice transition here.
So that's what this looks like.
You get a nice, smooth fade, even
on the iPad as Enrica showed you.
So our next step is to create this loading indicator.
You see it's static in this picture,
but actually animated as you saw.
So we want to be able to animate that.
Now there are two CSS effects we can use to get a
really nice, smoothly animating loading indicator here.
The first thing we can do is we can
use rotations by a CSS transforms
and the second one is we can use CSS
keyframe animations to have this animation
or this rotation continually repeat or continually animate.
And the benefit of doing it this way is: first of all,
you can do it without any plugins or animated JIFs;
you can use really nice, high-quality images,
maybe a PNG with alpha so it lends
very nicely with the rest of the page.
So let's see how we do this.
So here's our image.
And then to get the animation running,
there are two things we need to do.
The first one is we describe the
animation in terms of a set of keyframes.
So this uses a new at-rule and it has the -WebKit prefix.
So it's @-WebKit-keyframes.
And then the other name, spin, which we'll use later.
And the keyframes are where we
described the states of the animation.
So the front keyframe is the initial state
of this thing and it has a rotation of zero.
And then the 2 keyframe, the final state,
has a rotation of 360 degrees, so one turn.
And then as the animation's running, the
browser's going to interpolate between these two.
So they'll do a nice interpolation between 0 and
360, causing our image to spin around one time.
Now, it has this name "spin," which
is some name you give it.
And then you can apply the animation, using the
WebKit animation property, namely the keyframe, spin.
And then you give it a duration, so one second.
And that's the duration of one cycle of animation.
And in this case, we want this thing to spin around for
as long as we're waiting for that large image to load.
So the repeat count we use here is infinite.
But you could use 10 or 5 or 1 or whatever.
And we want it to spin with a constant angular
velocity so we use a linear timing function.
That gives us a nice, smooth spin out.
So that's pretty much all we need to do.
That gives us this nice spinning indicator.
And that spinning indicator is going to stay there for
as long as you're waiting for the large image to load.
But once that large image loads, then the next step
is to manage this transition to show the big image.
This is a little more complicated, so
I'm not going to go into all the details.
But the first thing you need to bear in mind is
we've got two things running here that are temporal:
we've got the large image loading and the overlay is fading.
And we need to have a little bit of logic in
our JavaScript that waits for both of these
to finish before we do this final reveal on the image.
And you can imagine you could use CSS transitions
on heightened width to do that scale of the image.
And if you wanted to, you could do transitions
of maybe opacity to reveal the caption
or maybe the caption could fall
down where the margin transition.
And you could reveal the close button
somehow, maybe it pops in with a scale.
So if you put all that stuff together, this is what it
looks like, although this is what it looks like on desktop.
On iPad, you probably wouldn't get a very good frame rate.
So let me talk a bit about optimizing for iPad and iPhone.
Now, as Enrica mentioned, if you were animating
properties with JavaScript, essentially --
many libraries do this, they're running timers
to change the style of an element, you know,
multiple times to get an animation to run.
The problem is the browser can't really optimize that
very well; it doesn't really know what the animation is.
So if you use CSS transitions in
animations, we can hit a fast path.
We know you're running an animation and
therefore, we can make it a lot more efficient.
And so you'll get at least as good performance
using transitions and animations on most properties
and you'll get significantly better performance if you
animate the transform property or the opacity properly
for these we actually make use of hardware acceleration.
We offload some of the compositing to the
GPU, so you get great performance with these
and these are really useful for iPad and iPhone.
So let me summarize what we learned
by building this better lightbox.
First of all, CSS transitions can give you a really nice
cinematic experience and they're really easy to offer.
Often it's just one line of the CSS to go from
a jarring transition to a nice, smooth one.
And you can get really good performance on all platforms.
Remember, the two properties you want to
stick to are WebKit-transform and opacity.
And then the second thing we learned is we can get
this nice, loading indicator using a combination
of a rotation transform and CSS animations
without any JavaScript, without any plugins.
So, you know, this lightbox is a
great way of showing a single image.
What if you want to show multiple images?
Well, that takes us into the next section, which
is building really awesome photo galleries.
And Enrica showed you some demos but here are
some of the effects we've put together here.
Now, some of these have a sense of
depth, they have some 3D in them.
And there are also some other kind of
interesting effects that we can get here.
So you'll see how to build these later in this session.
So before we delve into the details of
how to build a photo gallery like this,
I'd like to step back a little
bit and talk about best practices.
I think the most important thing when you're building
a photo gallery is to stay within the same page.
If you force people to load a new page for
every image as they go through a gallery,
that uses a lot of bandwidth, it's
very tedious for the user.
If they're on a slow connection, it will be really slow.
And there's no way you can do nice
transitions between images in that case.
And you may think, "Well, if you stay on
the same page doing kind of Ajax-y stuff,
don't you break history and bookmarking
and stuff like that?"
Well, HTML5 now has APIs that let you solve those problems
-- it has a history API and a location object you can use
to basically work around those
problems of bookmarking and history.
The second thing I recommend is: load each image on
demand; don't force the user to wait for all the images
in the gallery to load before they
can start stepping through it.
And with a little bit of JavaScript, you can just kick
off those image loads as the user's moving through.
It's quite straightforward.
A technique we found very useful when creating slightly more
complex content is to make extensive use of CSS class names
and specifically to use class names
to describe states in our content.
So in this particular example, we
have two types of state we care about.
When we're moving from one image to the next, we have a new
image that's coming in and we use an incoming class name
to identify that, and then the old image -- the one that's
going away -- and that gets the outgoing class name.
We also have the notion of initial and final states.
The initial state is where everything is before we start
running that transition from the old image to the new image.
And then the final state is where everything
is once we've finished that transition.
And now because we've described the states and the content
using class names, our JavaScript becomes very small.
Instead of having to write a lot of spaghetti JavaScript
that modifies style and does all this complicated stuff,
we can use the JavaScript for two really simple
things: the first is to kick off these image loads
so we have the dynamic image loading, and the second thing
that JavaScript does is just toggle these class names
to basically move us between the states
that we've already described in CSS.
So let's look at the actual markup or the structure
of the document we're going to use for this gallery.
We have the main div, which we call photo container,
which is just going to be the container
for the images we're showing.
And then when we're running a particular move from
one image to the next, we have an incoming image
which would give this class name incoming and the old
image that's going away gets the outgoing class name.
So temporarily, our photo container has two children
-- two child elements -- which are these two images.
And when the transition's done, we'll rip out
the old one and get left with just one image.
And of course to do this, so the images don't stack
up, you'd use absolute positioning and that kind
of thing so that they're in the right spot.
So bearing that in mind, let's see how we build
a transition like this, a push down transition.
So here's our photo container.
And now we start describing the states
of the content using these class names.
So the initial and final class names go on the photo
container because they apply to everything underneath it.
And then here we start styling the incoming image.
And we're using transforms, of course,
because we know they animate nicely.
In this case, we'll use translateY, which is just a
shorthand for a vertical translate and the value is -100%.
And that's a convenient way of
moving something up by its height.
So you can use percentages in translates
and that's pretty useful.
When the incoming image is in the final state,
it's front and center, it has a translateY(0).
And then the outgoing image starts in that same
spot and moves to a positive 100% translate.
So it goes down.
And then the final thing we want to do here is, of course,
tell the browser that all these style changes,
these state changes, should be animated.
So we use the transition property to specify that we
want transform to animate over a half-second here.
Now you may have noticed if you were
looking carefully in the previous slide
that we're also doing some opacity
changes as we're doing this transition.
I'm not showing this here for simplicity but
you can imagine it's pretty easy to add those.
So then there's some JavaScript we
need to actually do the image loading
and cause this transition to happen, so let's look at that.
So the first thing we do is getElementById that
just gives us a reference to our photo container.
And now we start setting these class names that
describe the states of things in our content.
So the outgoing image, the old image, we know
is the first child of the photo container
so we can add the outgoing class name to that one.
And we have the incoming image that's already
loaded so we set the incoming class name
on that and we're doing appendChild.
So now our photo container has two children.
And we set the initial class name to tell the browser
to render all those things in their initial states.
And we use the setTimeout technique again.
And all we have to do inside the setTimeout
is basically flip the class names.
So remove the initial class name, add the final class name,
and that will kick off all the transitions
that cause the effect to happen.
Now there's a little bit of clean
up we need to do at the end.
And the first thing we need to figure out was:
how do we know when this effect is finished,
when the move from the old image
to the new image is completed?
Well, transitions emit DOM events when they end.
So we can register an event listener, using an
event listener for the WebKit transition end event.
And we register a callback function
on that, which is transition done.
So let's write that now.
The first thing we do is remove the final class name.
We're done, the transition's over, we can just
remove the class names; we don't need them anymore.
And then we know the first child of the photo container
is the old image so we do a remove child, get rid of that.
And then we can just take the class name
off the incoming image because we're done.
Now the thing to note here is that this JavaScript
-- the JavaScript on the last two slides --
is not going to change for the rest of this session.
The JavaScript stays the same because
we've described all of the states in CSS.
So all we have to do is change the CSS to
get lots of different kinds of effects.
So let me show you some of those effects.
This is a scale transition -- we saw
Enrica demo it, it's very simple.
And here I'm just going to show you
the style for the incoming image,
the outgoing image is pretty much just the reverse.
So the incoming image starts with a
scale of zero, so it's like really tiny
in the middle and then it zooms up to a scale of 1.
And the outgoing image just does the reverse.
And then this funky spin transition.
Being an incoming image has initial rotation of
minus 180 degrees, that gives it a half turn.
And then its final rotation is zero.
And that's all we need to get that nice spin transition.
So let me summarize what we've
learned from photo gallery so far.
First of all, keep your user's window
the same page and then use JavaScript
to dynamically load images as you move through the gallery.
Use class names to describe states.
So use this declarative technique where all the interesting
states are described as combinations of CSS classes
and then your JavaScript becomes really small.
All your JavaScript's doing is toggling these classes.
And then to detect when transitions
end, use the transition end event.
And finally, all you have to do is change the
CSS to get lots of neat transition effects.
And transforms gives you all sorts of scales
and rotates you can do with the image.
So in this case we just used the transform property but
we were able to get lots of different kinds of effects.
So what about these effects that look
much more 3D to have this sense of depth?
Well, let's look at how to create these.
So, you know, these are obviously
doing some sort of 3D stuff.
What does this mean?
We have the ability to describe 3D transforms
in CSS now and this is pretty exciting.
So what it does really is it doesn't really
give us a sort of 3D modeling environment --
we don't have spheres and cubes and
cones and stuff but it does allow us
to position elements in a three-dimensional space.
Sometimes this is called "planes in space or 2.5D."
And this is -- in addition to the x- and
y-axes, you have for doing transforms already,
it gives you this z-axis, which is coming out of the screen.
So, just to look at the properties for a moment, this uses
the same transform property that we've been using already
but it has some new values, like
translate 3D, rotate 3D, scale 3D,
and then there's some convenient
versions of these like rotateX, rotateY.
Now 3D is a little more complex.
There's a little more setup you have to do to actually
make things look 3D and handle some other issues.
So the first property here that we
added is one called "perspective."
And this allows us to control a sense of depth in the scene.
And you'll see that in a moment.
The second one is useful - it's transform style --
is useful when you're building hierarchies of objects
and you want them to live in a
common three-dimensional space.
Transform style allows you to control
whether there's flattening
or whether these things live in a common 3D space.
And the other slightly odd thing with 3D transforms
is it's actually possible to flip an element
around so you can see the reverse side of it.
And sometimes you want that but sometimes you don't.
So back face visibility allows you to hide things
if they've definitely flipped all the way around.
So let's go back building a revolving
door effect using 3D transforms.
Now the first thing to note here is that with the revolving
door effect, it's like the hinges are on the right,
the elements are sort of swinging
around that right-hand edge.
So there's a little bit of setup
we have to do to make that work.
Now, she mentioned this in her session.
You can control the transform origin, in other
words, where the origin of the transform is,
and by default it's in the center of the element.
So if we rotated the element, you
noticed it rotated around the center.
We can use the transform origin property to change that.
So here we've used right 50%.
So that puts the transform origin on the right-hand edge.
And you can use pixel values, percentages,
or the keywords for this property.
So now when it rotates, it hinges about
that right edge, which is what we want.
And then, just as before, we use these class
names to set up the initial and the final states.
The incoming image is going to start basically
rotated into the screen from where the user is.
So that uses a rotation about the
y-axis, which is the vertical axis
of 90 degrees, which pushes it back into the screen.
And then the final state of the incoming
image is just flat on rotateY at 0.
And then the outgoing image, you can probably guess, starts
with the rotateY at 0 and then its final state is coming
out of the screen towards us, which
is rotateY of minus 90 degrees.
So if we actually put that together,
what would it look like?
Well, the answer is actually like this.
That was a revolving door.
This is an attempt at doing the cube transition.
And it looks very flat, you don't see any depth there.
And the reason is, we haven't described
any sort of depth in this scene.
So that's where we use this perspective
property that I mentioned before.
And what perspective does is it controls effectively
how far away the viewer is from the plane of the screen.
And the default value is NaN, which means the
viewer's infinitely far away, everything looks flat.
Then as we start setting that to actual
values -- it's like 4,000 pixels --
we start getting some amount of foreshortening in the scene.
And as the perspective gets smaller,
we get more and more foreshortening.
So it's as if you're getting closer and closer and
you've got really sort of wild 3D in this case.
So here we add the perspective and we get a nice 3D effect.
Now, there's one thing to note here, that perspective
is added on the photo container, not on the images.
Perspective affects the rendering of child
elements that have transformed in 3D.
Essentially, you can think of perspective as
setting up a 3D space for the elements underneath.
So far, all of the transitions we've done
have been simple blends, if you like,
between an initial state and a final state.
We've got some really neat ones, including
3D, but they're all just simple blends.
What if we want to do something a little
more complex, like this bats animation?
Well, this is another use for keyframe animations.
We saw a keyframe animation earlier because it gave us the
ability to have something that's continually repeating.
In this case, we're going to use keyframe animations
because they let us specify more
complex moves, using multiple keyframes.
And just like transitions, keyframe
animations emit DOM events when they complete
but also when they start and when they loop.
So we can hook into the same event notifications
to know when our transitions are complete.
So the actual properties, you've seen these already, the
@-WebKit-keyframes is where you set up the keyframes.
And then this is the longhand property here, animation
name, which is where you actually apply those keyframes.
One cycle of animation -- or duration of one cycle -- is
controlled by animation duration and the number of cycles
by animation duration count and this has that key word
"infinite" if you want to just keep going on forever.
And there's some other things you can do to control
the sort of behavior when the animation is repeating.
You can have every other cycle of animation go backwards
to give you some interesting back and forth behavior.
And then just like transitions, we
have an animation delay property.
And we'll see a really neat use case for that in a moment.
So let's build that drop animation using some keyframes.
Here's the initial div.
And I will set up these keyframes to describe the
states of the animation as the keyframe is running.
Our initial state -- or our from state or 0%, same thing --
is again, a translateY of -100%,
which puts the image above the box.
And then at 70% of the way through the animation,
it has a translateY(0), so it's down in the box.
And then this is how we do the little
bounce: we have an 83% keyframe that moves it
up by 10% and then it falls down again to 0%.
So that's enough to give us this nice little bounce effect.
And here we apply those keyframes, we're using
the shorthand here, animation drop 1 second.
So this is just going to run once over1 second.
Note that we didn't change any
JavaScript, so we're still using
that same JavaScript code you saw earlier in the session.
So we've got these two types of animation:
we've got transitions and keyframe animations.
And you're probably wondering why they
are two types and why isn't it just one?
So let me compare these to explain the differences.
Now the main difference is how they're triggered.
You saw from the lightbox example that we got this
nice overlay fade by changing opacity from 0 to 1
and because there was a transition rule in effect,
when the opacity changed, the transition ran.
So transitions are triggered by changes
in the underlying property values.
In other words, they run automatically but they're implicit.
Keyframe animations, on the other hand, run when they're
applied explicitly, using the animation name property.
So you put animation name on an element and as long as that
matches some keyframes, that element starts to animate.
So the notion with keyframe animations is you're really
using CSS to put an element into an animating state.
So that's quite different from transitions.
Both of these use timing functions for animations or
keyframe animations; the time function is within keyframes.
Of course, if you need keyframes, if you need
these more complex moves with multiple points
in them, keyframe animations are the way to go.
And they also allow you to have this repeating behavior,
which we used for the spinning
indicator and alternating behavior.
So far, the contents of our photo
gallery have just been images.
But since these effects apply to any HTML element --
and that include video, so we could put
video in our gallery if we wanted to.
We actually will -- you'll see that in a demo in a minute.
Or you could use SVG inside of HTML or Canvas or basically
any HTML content you can apply these CSS effects to.
This gives you a lot of scope, a lot
of capabilities to do neat stuff.
And actually, we're going to use
this now to create this tile effect.
And I'll show you how to build this tile effect.
But here effectively what we're doing
is where we had a single image before,
we're going to replace that with a little subtree
of nodes, using divs, to give us the tile effect.
So the way we create these tile effects
are to build a div and we're going to call
that "tile container" just so we can style it.
And tile container is the container for this grid of tiles.
So each of these is a div itself.
And then the way we tessellate them to
make it look like they're a single image is
to use background position and to set a background image.
And so we use background position to make sure that
the right part of the image is rendered into each tile.
So this is a kind of thing you
could do in mock-up if you wanted --
you could have 16 or 24 tiles as divs in your HTML content.
But this type of repetitive stuff is much
better done with little bit of JavaScript.
So this is the script you would
write to generate these tiles.
So we're just iterating through the rows and
columns and for each tile, creating a div element.
And then we compute whether elements positioned inside
the grid based on the row and column and the tile height
and the tile width, which we know in advance.
And then the tiles are absolutely positioned
so we can position very easily to form a grid
and we do that by setting the left and top properties.
And then here's the key to make
it look like it's a single image.
We set the background image property, and here I've used
a hard-coded image but you probably use the next image
in your slide show, which you'd feed into this function.
And then you set the background image property to
minus tileX, minus tileY and that gets the correct part
of the image rendered into this particular tile.
So the next thing we do -- we've got this grid of tiles --
we want to cause these tiles to
animate in some interesting way.
And in this case we'll use a drop animation,
which is very similar to the one we just saw.
But before we were running it on a single image;
here it's running on each individual tile.
So this is the same set of keyframes.
There's a slight difference here,
which is they've both added opacity.
So here opacity is going to animate
between the 0% and 70% keyframes.
This just shows you that it's possible to animate
multiple properties inside of keyframes --
you're not limited to animating just one.
And then here's where we apply the animation.
The selector's a little more complex because we have
to apply this to the divs, which are direct children
of the tile container when the tile
container's in the incoming state.
So if we actually did that, this is what it would look like.
And we didn't see any tiles.
You know, what's up?
Well, we've got this grid of tiles but
they're all animating at the same time,
they're all in synchrony, so they just fall down as a block.
And that doesn't really look very interesting.
So we can add one more line to our JavaScript loop.
And that line is going to set animation delay.
So just as in the previous session, you saw a use
of transition delay that causes menus to build in;
here we set animation delay to cause things
to happen at slightly different times.
And we're making use of Math.random,
which is a JavaScript function
that gives you back a random number between 0 and 1.
So this sets animation delay to somewhere between
0 and 1 second, independently for each tile.
So now when we run the transition,
we get this really cool effect.
So just to summarize what we've learned from this tile
effect stuff: we can replace the single image in our gallery
with a grid of tile elements or a grid of divs representing
tiles, and use background image and background position
to have each tile render the right part of the image.
And then we see how useful delays are.
In the previous session, you saw
transition delay being put to good use
and here animation delay is really great
for doing these neat build effects.
So at this point, I'd like to invite
Enrica back to show you the gallery
that we got when we put all of this stuff together.
[ Applause ]
>> Enrica Casucci: Hi again.
So we're back to our photo gallery example
that we have seen before on my iPad.
But this time we're going to make a look at it from a Mac.
So here is a photo gallery and you've just learned
from Simon how easy it is to combine CSS transforms
and animations to create a series of amazing effects.
And you know, we have seen how easy it is to create a
crossfade, a push, or a push down, scale transforms.
I want you to really appreciate, in this case we are using
larger images than the ones we have used for the iPad demo.
And notice how smooth the transition
is, even with these larger images.
But what really makes a difference is when you start using
the 3D transforms because not only you create, you know,
some very cool effects like this one, but it also opens
up a world of possibilities in terms of what you can do
to present additional content that
is related to your images.
Let's say for example you want to show some
text or date associated with the picture.
And so why not simply flip the
image on the back and show it?
Isn't that cool?
[ Applause ]
We've seen the revolving door, the swap, and the cube.
And remember, all these transitions
that we have seen up to this point,
they all use the same JavaScript;
we've only changed the CSS.
And as Simon mentioned, with HTML5, video elements
have become first-class citizens in the web world.
So all these effects that we have seen apply
to images can be applied to video elements
as well, and we can have something like this.
Notice that the video is playing.
I can still flip it on the back and show my additional
information while the video is still playing.
[ Applause ]
Look, now that I'm showing you the transition
in slow motion that you can really appreciate
that the video is playing while
the transition is taking place.
I think this is absolutely awesome.
Then with a little bit of JavaScript, you can easily
create this fantastic tiling effect that you have seen.
And, you know, this is just a combination of rotation
with the same technique you have seen before.
But now that you know how to slice
up the images, the sky's the limit.
You can create unfolding effects like this one or this one
that you got a sneak preview before or something like this.
This is when you're supposed to do "Wow."
[ Applause ]
Let me show it to you one more time in slow motion so
you can fully appreciate how smooth the transition is.
>> Wow.
>> Enrica Casucci: Thank you.
That's what I wanted to hear.
[ Laughter ]
[ Applause ]
I hope at this point I got you
all fired up and I hope I was able
to communicate the excitement I have for this technology.
We have some great labs tomorrow and we hope to see you all
there and come over and start playing with our sample code.
I'll give you back to Simon.
That is going to wrap up the session.
Thank you.
[ Applause ]
>> Simone Fraser: Thank you, Enrica.
I think that really was an awesome photo gallery.
So let me just take a moment to summarize
where these things are supported.
So I talked about four categories of CSS effects today:
2D transforms, 3D transforms, transitions, and animations.
And all of these are supported on
iPhone and iPad since iPhone 2.0.
Safari on Mac has supported all of these
since Safari 4 and now with Safari 5,
we have support across the board on Mac and Windows.
And then Chrome supports these;
they don't have 3D rendering.
And some of the other browsers are catching up too, now
-- Opera and Firefox have 2D transforms and transitions.
So let me summarize what we've learned in today's session.
First of all, using CSS transitions and animations, you can
get really neat animations with very little authoring work.
In many cases, it's just one line of CSS to go
from a jarring transition to a nice, smooth one.
And you can get great performance
even on devices like iPhone and iPad.
And you'll get generally much better
performance than you would if you used one
of the JavaScript libraries that's running
JavaScript time as to do animation.
And then with CSS transforms, we can position elements and
transform them both in two dimensions and three dimensions.
And as Enrica mentioned, this opens all sorts of
possibilities for interesting ways of user interaction,
flipping things around, building
things like cubes and rings.
And you've probably seen a bunch of examples
and there's a lot of sample code for this.
But another great thing about animations
-- sorry, about transforms --
is that they work very well with transitions and animations.
By running transitions between
different types of 3D transforms,
you can get all sorts of really cool effects
and the animations run really smoothly.
So there's a great synergy between these two things.
And finally, not just images but as you saw,
we can have great performance running these
on video as well and any other HTML element.
So for more information, you can contact Vicki
Murley, the Safari Technologies Evangelist.
And there's great documentation on the Safari Dev Center.
If you want to go and look at the CSS specifications
and follow the workings of the CSS working group,
you can look at the current work page there.
And then the Apple developer forums are
another great place to go and get help.